<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<appendix role="normative" id="annexA">
  <title>License, Document Status and Notices</title>

  <section id="documentStatus">
    <title>Document Status</title>

    <para>This document was last revised or approved by the OASIS XLIFF TC on the above date.
      The level of approval is also listed above. Check the "Latest version" location noted
      above for possible later revisions of this document. Any other numbered Versions and
      other technical work produced by the Technical Committee (TC) are listed at <ulink
        url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf#technical"
        >https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf#technical</ulink>.</para>

    <para>TC members should send comments on this document to the TC's email list. Others
      should send comments to the TC's public comment list, after subscribing to it by
      following the comment instructions at the TC's comments list web page at <ulink
        url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=xliff"
        >https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=xliff</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="licenseAndNotices">
    <title>License and Notices</title>

    <para>Copyright © OASIS Open &pubyear;. All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings assigned to them in the
      OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the "OASIS IPR Policy"). The full Policy, which
      governs the licensure of this document, may be found at the OASIS website: [<ulink
        url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/"
        >https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/</ulink>]</para>

    <para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to others, and
      derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it or assist in its implementation
      may be prepared, copied, published, and distributed, in whole or in part, without
      restriction of any kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this section are
      included on all such copies and derivative works. However, this document itself may not
      be modified in any way, including by removing the copyright notice or references to
      OASIS, except as needed for the purpose of developing any document or deliverable
      produced by an OASIS Technical Committee (in which case the rules applicable to
      copyrights, as set forth in the OASIS IPR Policy, must be followed) or as required to
      translate it into languages other than English.</para>

    <para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be revoked by OASIS
      or its successors or assigns, as provided in the OASIS IPR Policy.</para>

    <para>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an "AS IS" basis
      and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY
      WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP RIGHTS OR
      ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. OASIS AND
      ITS MEMBERS WILL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
      ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THIS DOCUMENT OR ANY PART THEREOF.</para>

    <para>The name "OASIS" is a trademark of OASIS, the owner and developer of this document,
      and should be used only to refer to the organization and its official outputs. OASIS
      welcomes reference to, and implementation and use of, its documents, while reserving the
      right to enforce its marks against misleading uses. Please see <ulink
        url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/"
        >https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/</ulink> for guidance.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
