<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="exchange">
  <title>Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</title>

  <para>An XLIFF document is bilingual: it declares a single <code>srcLang</code> and a single
    <code>trgLang</code>. A translation memory, however, is often required to hold or exchange
    content across more than two languages. TMX addresses this within a single file, because a
    <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> can hold any number of <code>&lt;tuv&gt;</code> elements, one per
    language.</para>

  <para>This document recommends addressing the same requirement not by making an individual
    XLIFF document multilingual, which would be a departure from the XLIFF Core data model, but
    by packaging multiple bilingual XLIFF files together, one per source/target language pair,
    along with a manifest that identifies the relationship among them. This keeps every
    individual file fully conformant with, and processable by, any existing XLIFF 2.x tool,
    while still allowing a translation memory covering many languages to be exchanged as a
    single unit.</para>

  <para>A multilingual translation memory is rarely built from a single source language: it
    typically accumulates from projects extracted from whatever source language each originating
    document happened to use. Accordingly, the files in a package are not required to share a
    common <code>srcLang</code>. A single package MAY combine bilingual files representing any
    number of independent source/target language pairs, for example an
    <code>en-es.xlf</code> file alongside an unrelated <code>fr-de.xlf</code> file, with the
    manifest simply recording the <code>srcLang</code> and <code>trgLang</code> that each file
    declares.</para>

  <section id="packageStructure">
    <title>Package Structure</title>

    <para>A translation memory exchange package is a ZIP archive (as defined in [ZIP APPNOTE])
      with the following content:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more bilingual XLIFF files, each conforming to [XLIFF-2.3-part2] or later,
          each independently declaring its own <code>srcLang</code> and <code>trgLang</code>.
          Files in the same package are not required to share a common
          <code>srcLang</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A single manifest file, described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml"
            targetptr="manifestFile">Manifest File</olink>, that groups the XLIFF files in the
          package into one or more aligned sets by shared source language and records the
          language pair each file represents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The XLIFF files in a package are not required to sit at the root of the archive. They
      MAY instead be organized into any folder structure the package author finds convenient, for
      example one folder per language pair. The manifest's <code>href</code> value for each file
      gives that file's actual path within the package, so a consumer locates every file through
      the manifest rather than by assuming a particular layout.</para>

    <para>Every file listed in the manifest belongs to exactly one aligned set: a group of files
      that share a common <code>srcLang</code> and were extracted from the same source content.
      A file with no counterpart sharing its source is simply the only member of its own aligned
      set. Corresponding translation units across the files in an aligned set MUST use the same
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> <code>id</code> value (and, where segmented, the same
      <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> <code>id</code> value). This is what lets a consumer treat
      aligned-set membership as a guarantee rather than a hint: a match against a given
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> <code>id</code> in one file of the set is known to correspond to
      the same source context in every other file of the set, which lets a tool synthesize a
      multi-target match across every language in the set directly from a single-language
      lookup, without re-querying each file separately. This mirrors, at the package level, the
      alignment that a multilingual <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> provides in a single TMX file, while
      extending it to packages whose source language differs from one aligned set to the
      next.</para>

    <para>A tool that does not support this manifest format is not prevented from using the
      package. Because every file it lists remains an independent, fully conformant XLIFF
      document, such a tool MAY simply extract the archive, ignore <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code>,
      and ingest each bilingual XLIFF file on its own, exactly as it would ingest any other XLIFF
      file it was given individually. The manifest adds cross-file structure for tools that
      understand it; it is not required to make the package's contents usable.</para>

    <para>The same fallback applies if a ZIP archive of bilingual XLIFF files has no
      <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code> at all: such an archive does not conform to this document
      as a Translation Memory Exchange Package, but a tool MAY still treat it as an unlinked
      collection of independent bilingual memories and ingest each file individually.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="manifestFile">
    <title>Manifest File</title>

    <para>The manifest is an XML file, named <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code>, placed at the root of
      the package. Its root <code>&lt;tmPackage&gt;</code> element MAY carry a
      <code>packageId</code> attribute identifying the package and a <code>created</code>
      attribute recording when it was assembled; both are informational and carry no processing
      requirement. It groups the package's XLIFF files into one or more
      <code>&lt;alignedSet&gt;</code> elements, each declaring the shared <code>srcLang</code> of
      its members and MAY carry a <code>&lt;description&gt;</code> child element with a
      human-readable summary of what the set represents. Within an aligned set, each file is
      listed as a <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> element giving the <code>href</code> path to the file
      within the package and the <code>trgLang</code> it represents, and MAY carry a
      <code>hash</code> attribute so a consumer can verify the file was not corrupted or altered
      in transit.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0"
    packageId="pkg-2026-finance-tm" created="2026-07-10T13:43:00Z"&gt;
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-01" srcLang="en"&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;Financial terminology memory extracted from Q2 2026 projects.&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;file href="en-es.xlf" trgLang="es"
      hash="sha256:3451e18e0aa54c65398509e1decd963e1ea1fafa4dee37fde6b1e2585c0f74ec"/&gt;
    &lt;file href="en-fr.xlf" trgLang="fr"
      hash="sha256:ec076145e71a8c08b9e78253ceac02bc9a0f98a56577216987ab6dea15e7b457"/&gt;
  &lt;/alignedSet&gt;
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-02" srcLang="fr"&gt;
    &lt;file href="fr-de.xlf" trgLang="de"
      hash="sha256:6dc9abf3aace245aefb08f4220e8355dc237de9ef289c60c87abd734ed552986"/&gt;
  &lt;/alignedSet&gt;
&lt;/tmPackage&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>A manifest is not required to declare the same <code>srcLang</code> for every aligned
      set it contains, as the example above illustrates: <code>en-es.xlf</code> and
      <code>en-fr.xlf</code> both originate from English source content and are grouped together
      in <code>set-01</code>, while <code>fr-de.xlf</code> is an unrelated bilingual file with
      French as its source language and forms the single-member <code>set-02</code> on its
      own.</para>

    <para>The <code>hash</code> attribute lets an exchanging tool make two decisions before it
      opens or parses a potentially large XLIFF file. When synchronizing against a package it
      has seen before, a tool can compare a file's <code>hash</code> value in the new manifest
      against the hash of the copy it already holds, and skip reparsing entirely when they
      match, rather than reparsing every file on every sync. After extracting a file from the
      archive, a tool can also recompute its hash and compare it against the value recorded in
      the manifest to detect truncation or corruption introduced during transport, before that
      file's content is allowed to reach a TM store.</para>

    <para>A <code>hash</code> value is expressed as <code>algorithm:digest</code>, where
      <code>algorithm</code> identifies the hash function used (<code>sha256</code> is
      RECOMMENDED) and <code>digest</code> is the lowercase hexadecimal digest it produces. Where
      a <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> entry carries a <code>hash</code> value, an exchanging tool
      SHOULD validate the extracted file's content against it before committing that content to
      a TM store, and SHOULD treat a mismatch as a sign of a corrupted or incomplete transfer
      rather than importing it. A matching hash only guards against accidental
      corruption in transport: because both a file and its manifest entry are typically produced
      by the same party, a hash alone does not protect against deliberate tampering by anyone
      able to modify the package.</para>

    <para><emphasis>The manifest namespace, element and attribute names, and XML Schema shown
      above are provisional and subject to review by the OASIS XLIFF TC before this Note
      advances beyond Committee Note Draft.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="exchangeExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A translation memory accumulated from an English-source project translated into
      Spanish and French, together with an unrelated project whose source was French and whose
      target was German, would be packaged as:</para>

    <programlisting>tm-package.zip
├── xliff-manifest.xml
├── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr.xlf
└── fr-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>Each of <code>en-es.xlf</code>, <code>en-fr.xlf</code>, and <code>fr-de.xlf</code> is
      an ordinary bilingual XLIFF document as described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml"
        targetptr="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</olink>, and each can be
      consumed independently by a tool that only needs one language pair, or together by a tool
      that reads <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code> to reconstruct the full set. <code>en-es.xlf</code>
      and <code>en-fr.xlf</code> share a common source language and belong to the same aligned
      set, so they MUST be aligned by <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code>
      <code>id</code> as described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml"
        targetptr="packageStructure">Package Structure</olink>; <code>fr-de.xlf</code> has no
      source language in common with the other two files and forms its own aligned set, outside
      that alignment.</para>

    <para>As described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml" targetptr="packageStructure">Package
        Structure</olink>, the same three files MAY instead be organized into one folder per
      language pair:</para>

    <programlisting>tm-package.zip
├── xliff-manifest.xml
├── en-es/
│   └── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr/
│   └── en-fr.xlf
└── fr-de/
    └── fr-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>with the manifest updated to match:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0"
    packageId="pkg-2026-finance-tm" created="2026-07-10T13:43:00Z"&gt;
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-01" srcLang="en"&gt;
    &lt;file href="en-es/en-es.xlf" trgLang="es"
      hash="sha256:3451e18e0aa54c65398509e1decd963e1ea1fafa4dee37fde6b1e2585c0f74ec"/&gt;
    &lt;file href="en-fr/en-fr.xlf" trgLang="fr"
      hash="sha256:ec076145e71a8c08b9e78253ceac02bc9a0f98a56577216987ab6dea15e7b457"/&gt;
  &lt;/alignedSet&gt;
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-02" srcLang="fr"&gt;
    &lt;file href="fr-de/fr-de.xlf" trgLang="de"
      hash="sha256:6dc9abf3aace245aefb08f4220e8355dc237de9ef289c60c87abd734ed552986"/&gt;
  &lt;/alignedSet&gt;
&lt;/tmPackage&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Both layouts are valid and equivalent: a conformant consumer resolves every file
      through the <code>href</code> value recorded in the manifest rather than by assuming
      either layout.</para>
  </section>
</section>
