<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="exchange">
  <title>Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</title>

  <para>An XLIFF document is bilingual: it declares a single <code>srcLang</code> and a single
    <code>trgLang</code>. A translation memory, however, is often required to hold or exchange
    content across more than two languages. TMX addresses this within a single file, because a
    <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> can hold any number of <code>&lt;tuv&gt;</code> elements, one per
    language.</para>

  <para>This document recommends addressing the same requirement not by making an individual
    XLIFF document multilingual, which would be a departure from the XLIFF Core data model, but
    by packaging multiple bilingual XLIFF files together, one per source/target language pair,
    along with a manifest that identifies the relationship among them. This keeps every
    individual file fully conformant with, and processable by, any existing XLIFF 2.x tool,
    while still allowing a translation memory covering many languages to be exchanged as a
    single unit.</para>

  <section id="packageStructure">
    <title>Package Structure</title>

    <para>A translation memory exchange package is a ZIP archive (as defined in [ZIP APPNOTE])
      with the following content:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more bilingual XLIFF files, each conforming to [XLIFF-2.2-part2] or later,
          sharing a common <code>srcLang</code> and each declaring its own
          <code>trgLang</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A single manifest file, described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml"
            targetptr="manifestFile">Manifest File</olink>, that lists the XLIFF files in the
          package and the language pair each one represents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Corresponding translation units across the language-pair files in a package SHOULD
      use the same <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> <code>id</code> value (and, where segmented, the
      same <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> <code>id</code> value) so that a consumer can align
      entries for the same source content across target languages. This mirrors, at the
      package level, the alignment that a multilingual <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> provides in a
      single TMX file.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="manifestFile">
    <title>Manifest File</title>

    <para>The manifest is an XML file, named <code>manifest.xml</code>, placed at the root of
      the package. It lists each XLIFF file contained in the package together with its source
      and target language.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0">
  <file href="en-es.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="es"/>
  <file href="en-fr.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="fr"/>
  <file href="en-de.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="de"/>
</tmPackage>]]></programlisting>

    <para><emphasis>The manifest namespace, element and attribute names, and XML Schema shown
      above are provisional and subject to review by the OASIS XLIFF TC before this Note
      advances beyond Committee Note Draft.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="exchangeExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A translation memory covering English source content with Spanish, French, and
      German target content would be packaged as:</para>

    <programlisting>tm-package.zip
├── manifest.xml
├── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr.xlf
└── en-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>Each of <code>en-es.xlf</code>, <code>en-fr.xlf</code>, and <code>en-de.xlf</code> is
      an ordinary bilingual XLIFF document as described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml"
        targetptr="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</olink>, and each can be
      consumed independently by a tool that only needs one language pair, or together by a tool
      that reads <code>manifest.xml</code> to reconstruct the full multilingual set.</para>
  </section>
</section>
