<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="exchange">
  <title>Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</title>

  <para>An XLIFF document is bilingual: it declares a single <code>srcLang</code> and a single
    <code>trgLang</code>. A translation memory, however, is often required to hold or exchange
    content across more than two languages. TMX addresses this within a single file, because a
    <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> can hold any number of <code>&lt;tuv&gt;</code> elements, one per
    language.</para>

  <para>This document recommends addressing the same requirement not by making an individual
    XLIFF document multilingual, which would be a departure from the XLIFF Core data model, but
    by packaging multiple bilingual XLIFF files together, one per source/target language pair,
    along with a manifest that identifies the relationship among them. This keeps every
    individual file fully conformant with, and processable by, any existing XLIFF 2.x tool,
    while still allowing a translation memory covering many languages to be exchanged as a
    single unit.</para>

  <para>A multilingual translation memory is rarely built from a single source language: it
    typically accumulates from projects extracted from whatever source language each originating
    document happened to use. Accordingly, the files in a package are not required to share a
    common <code>srcLang</code>. A single package MAY combine bilingual files representing any
    number of independent source/target language pairs, for example an
    <code>en-es.xlf</code> file alongside an unrelated <code>fr-de.xlf</code> file, with the
    manifest simply recording the <code>srcLang</code> and <code>trgLang</code> that each file
    declares.</para>

  <section id="packageStructure">
    <title>Package Structure</title>

    <para>A translation memory exchange package is a ZIP archive (as defined in [ZIP APPNOTE])
      with the following content:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more bilingual XLIFF files, each conforming to [XLIFF-2.3-part2] or later,
          each independently declaring its own <code>srcLang</code> and <code>trgLang</code>.
          Files in the same package are not required to share a common
          <code>srcLang</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A single manifest file, described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml"
            targetptr="manifestFile">Manifest File</olink>, that lists the XLIFF files in the
          package and the language pair each one represents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The XLIFF files in a package are not required to sit at the root of the archive. They
      MAY instead be organized into any folder structure the package author finds convenient, for
      example one folder per language pair. The manifest's <code>href</code> value for each file
      gives that file's actual path within the package, so a consumer locates every file through
      the manifest rather than by assuming a particular layout.</para>

    <para>Where two or more files in a package share the same <code>srcLang</code> and were
      extracted from the same source content, corresponding translation units across those
      files SHOULD use the same <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> <code>id</code> value (and, where
      segmented, the same <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> <code>id</code> value), so that a
      consumer can align entries for the same source content across target languages. This
      mirrors, at the package level, the alignment that a multilingual <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code>
      provides in a single TMX file for that case. This alignment applies only among files that
      share a source: it does not extend across files with different <code>srcLang</code>
      values, whose <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> <code>id</code>
      values are independent of one another.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="manifestFile">
    <title>Manifest File</title>

    <para>The manifest is an XML file, named <code>manifest.xml</code>, placed at the root of
      the package. It lists each XLIFF file contained in the package, together with its source
      and target language, using an <code>href</code> value that gives the file's path within
      the package.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0"&gt;
  &lt;file href="en-es.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="es"/&gt;
  &lt;file href="en-fr.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="fr"/&gt;
  &lt;file href="fr-de.xlf" srcLang="fr" trgLang="de"/&gt;
&lt;/tmPackage&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>A manifest is not required to declare the same <code>srcLang</code> for every file it
      lists, as the third entry above illustrates: <code>en-es.xlf</code> and
      <code>en-fr.xlf</code> both originate from English source content, while
      <code>fr-de.xlf</code> is an unrelated bilingual file with French as its source
      language.</para>

    <para><emphasis>The manifest namespace, element and attribute names, and XML Schema shown
      above are provisional and subject to review by the OASIS XLIFF TC before this Note
      advances beyond Committee Note Draft.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="exchangeExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A translation memory accumulated from an English-source project translated into
      Spanish and French, together with an unrelated project whose source was French and whose
      target was German, would be packaged as:</para>

    <programlisting>tm-package.zip
├── manifest.xml
├── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr.xlf
└── fr-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>Each of <code>en-es.xlf</code>, <code>en-fr.xlf</code>, and <code>fr-de.xlf</code> is
      an ordinary bilingual XLIFF document as described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml"
        targetptr="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</olink>, and each can be
      consumed independently by a tool that only needs one language pair, or together by a tool
      that reads <code>manifest.xml</code> to reconstruct the full set. <code>en-es.xlf</code>
      and <code>en-fr.xlf</code> share a common source language and MAY be aligned by
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> <code>id</code> as described in
      <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml" targetptr="packageStructure">Package Structure</olink>;
      <code>fr-de.xlf</code> has no source language in common with the other two files and is
      not part of that alignment.</para>

    <para>As described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml" targetptr="packageStructure">Package
        Structure</olink>, the same three files MAY instead be organized into one folder per
      language pair:</para>

    <programlisting>tm-package.zip
├── manifest.xml
├── en-es/
│   └── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr/
│   └── en-fr.xlf
└── fr-de/
    └── fr-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>with the manifest updated to match:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0"&gt;
  &lt;file href="en-es/en-es.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="es"/&gt;
  &lt;file href="en-fr/en-fr.xlf" srcLang="en" trgLang="fr"/&gt;
  &lt;file href="fr-de/fr-de.xlf" srcLang="fr" trgLang="de"/&gt;
&lt;/tmPackage&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Both layouts are valid and equivalent: a conformant consumer resolves every file
      through the <code>href</code> value recorded in the manifest rather than by assuming
      either layout.</para>
  </section>
</section>
