<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="implementation">
  <title>Creating and Searching a Translation Memory Store</title>

  <para>This section is informative and does not define conformance requirements. It describes
    practical, non-mandatory approaches for creating and querying a translation memory store as
    described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation
    Memory Format</olink>. Implementers MAY use either of these approaches, a combination of
    them, or an approach not described here; this document does not mandate a particular storage
    or retrieval technology.</para>

  <para>The packaging convention described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml"
      targetptr="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</olink> is intended
    for exchanging translation memory data between parties and tools, not as an implementation
    architecture. An implementation is not expected to query a ZIP package directly: it typically
    loads the bilingual XLIFF files it receives, or the ones it produces by harvesting as
    described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="harvesting">Harvesting Translation
      Memory Entries</olink>, into whichever storage and retrieval mechanism it uses internally,
    of which the following are two examples.</para>

  <note>
    <title>Fuzzy Search Versus Semantic Search</title>

    <para>The two approaches described in this section answer different questions. Fuzzy
      search, as provided by an XML-aware database (through XPath/XQuery string functions or a
      similarity extension) or by a SQL database (through trigram indexes, edit-distance
      functions, or full-text search), measures how similar two strings are as sequences of
      characters. It reliably finds near-duplicates that differ by a word, a typo, or a small
      edit, but has no notion of meaning: it can rank a sentence whose negation flips its meaning
      as a close match to the original, and it will not find a paraphrase that shares no wording
      at all.</para>

    <para>Semantic search, as provided by a vector database over text embeddings, measures how
      similar two passages are in meaning, independent of wording. It finds paraphrases that a
      fuzzy search misses, but is not guaranteed to penalize a small, meaning-changing edit as
      heavily as a fuzzy search would, since embeddings can place semantically related but
      contradictory statements close together in vector space. This complementary blind spot is
      why <olink targetdoc="implementation.xml" targetptr="vectorDatabaseApproach">Vector
        Database and Similarity Search</olink> recommends blending a semantic score with a fuzzy
      score rather than relying on either alone.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Organizations with an existing SQL-based translation memory engine, many of which
    already parse a source/target pair out of a TMX <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;tuv&gt;</code>
    and store it in relational tables, do not need to replace that engine to work with a store
    described in this document: the same import step can instead read
    <code>&lt;source&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;target&gt;</code> content directly out of XLIFF
    <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> elements. This is a low-effort migration path that reuses
    existing search and scoring logic, but on its own it does not bring the context-aware
    retrieval described in <olink targetdoc="implementation.xml"
      targetptr="xmlDatabaseApproach">XML-Aware Database and XPath Retrieval</olink> or the
    paraphrase-level retrieval described in <olink targetdoc="implementation.xml"
      targetptr="vectorDatabaseApproach">Vector Database and Similarity Search</olink>: a
    relational schema built around a flat source/target pair typically discards the same
    document order, <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> origin, and grouping that a flat TMX export
    discards, unless the importer is extended to capture them as additional columns.</para>

  <section id="xmlDatabaseApproach">
    <title>XML-Aware Database and XPath Retrieval</title>

    <para>Because a translation memory store described in this document is plain, well-formed
      XLIFF, it can be loaded directly into an XML-aware database and queried with XPath or
      XQuery, without any transformation of its content. A query can match on
      <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> text, restrict candidates to a particular
      <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> <code>original</code> value or Provenance attribute as described
      in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for
        Translation Memory Entries</olink>, or exploit the preserved document order described in
      <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="structuralOrder">Structural Order and Segment
        Context</olink> to retrieve a match together with its neighboring segments.</para>

    <para>Examples of XML-aware databases that support this style of storage and query include,
      without limitation, BaseX, eXist-db, MarkLogic, and Oracle XML DB. Naming these products is
      illustrative only and does not constitute an endorsement or a requirement to use any of
      them.</para>

    <para>For example, the following excerpt of a translation memory store, taken from the store
      shown in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="tmFormatExample">Example</olink>,
      contains two entries with identical source text, harvested from two different
      documents:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;file id="f1" original="manual/chapter3.html"&gt;
  &lt;unit id="tm-0002"&gt;
    &lt;segment&gt;
      &lt;source&gt;Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source&gt;
      &lt;target&gt;Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target&gt;
    &lt;/segment&gt;
  &lt;/unit&gt;
&lt;/file&gt;
&lt;file id="f2" original="app/ui-strings.json"&gt;
  &lt;unit id="tm-1001"&gt;
    &lt;segment&gt;
      &lt;source&gt;Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source&gt;
      &lt;target&gt;Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target&gt;
    &lt;/segment&gt;
  &lt;/unit&gt;
&lt;/file&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>An XPath query that matches on source text alone:</para>

    <programlisting>//unit[segment/source = 'Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.']</programlisting>

    <para>returns both <code>tm-0002</code> and <code>tm-1001</code>, since both segments share
      the same exact source text. If the unit currently being translated originated from
      <code>manual/chapter3.html</code>, the query can be narrowed to prefer an in-context exact
      match, as described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="structuralOrder">Structural
        Order and Segment Context</olink>, by also constraining the enclosing
      <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> element's <code>original</code> attribute:</para>

    <programlisting>//file[@original = 'manual/chapter3.html']
    /unit[segment/source = 'Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.']</programlisting>

    <para>which returns only <code>tm-0002</code>, the entry harvested from the same document as
      the unit being translated.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="vectorDatabaseApproach">
    <title>Vector Database and Similarity Search</title>

    <para>Alternatively, the <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> (and, where useful,
      <code>&lt;target&gt;</code>) text of each harvested <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> can be
      converted to a numeric embedding by a text embedding model and indexed in a vector
      database, with each vector referencing the <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> and
      <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> it was derived from. Retrieval is then performed as a similarity
      search over embeddings rather than an exact or XPath-based text match, which can surface
      fuzzy matches that share meaning but not exact wording. As with the XML-database approach,
      the enclosing <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> <code>original</code> attribute and Provenance
      metadata remain available as filters that can be applied alongside, or after, the
      similarity search to narrow candidates.</para>

    <para>Examples of vector databases that support this style of retrieval include, without
      limitation, LanceDB, Milvus, Weaviate, Qdrant, and pgvector, a vector extension for
      PostgreSQL. Naming these products is illustrative only and does not constitute an
      endorsement or a requirement to use any of them.</para>

    <para>Continuing the example from <olink targetdoc="implementation.xml"
        targetptr="xmlDatabaseApproach">XML-Aware Database and XPath Retrieval</olink>, the same
      two entries could instead be indexed as vectors, each referencing the
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> and originating <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> it was derived from
      (embedding values abbreviated for illustration):</para>

    <programlisting>tm-0002  original=manual/chapter3.html  "Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year."  [0.114, -0.028, 0.301, ...]
tm-1001  original=app/ui-strings.json   "Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year."  [0.109, -0.031, 0.298, ...]</programlisting>

    <para>Unlike an XPath query, a similarity search is not limited to exact text. A query using
      a paraphrase of the same request, which shares no exact wording with either stored
      segment:</para>

    <programlisting>"Please download your tax certificate before the fiscal year ends."</programlisting>

    <para>is converted to an embedding and compared against the indexed vectors, returning both
      <code>tm-0002</code> and <code>tm-1001</code> ranked by similarity score (for example,
      0.93 for each), even though an XPath query for this exact string, as in <olink
        targetdoc="implementation.xml" targetptr="xmlDatabaseApproach">XML-Aware Database and
        XPath Retrieval</olink>, would return no results at all. As in that example, restricting
      the search to vectors whose <code>original</code> metadata equals
      <code>manual/chapter3.html</code> narrows the result to <code>tm-0002</code> alone.</para>

    <para>Semantic similarity alone has a known blind spot: embeddings can rank a candidate that
      changes the meaning nearly as highly as one that only changes the wording. Combining
      semantic similarity with a string-similarity ("fuzzy") metric into a single blended score,
      rather than using either alone, addresses this: a fuzzy string comparison of the same
      candidates penalizes that difference, while still tolerating the minor spelling or
      punctuation variation that an exact-text query would reject outright. Blending the two, for
      example by averaging a semantic similarity score with a string-similarity score such as
      longest-common-subsequence, gives a single ranking that neither method reliably produces on
      its own.</para>

    <para>A vector database's own distance metric only measures how similar a candidate is to
      the query; it has no notion of what that candidate cost to produce. Where a harvested
      entry's <code>&lt;pvn:provenance&gt;</code> chain, described in <olink
        targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for
        Translation Memory Entries</olink>, includes a <code>&lt;pvn:usage&gt;</code> element,
      implementers SHOULD map its text value alongside its <code>usageUnit</code> attribute as
      additional metadata fields on the indexed vector. Because <code>&lt;pvn:usage&gt;</code>
      records the computational cost of producing a change, for example the number of tokens a
      machine translation agent consumed to generate a target, a similarity search can then
      weight or filter candidates by that cost in addition to similarity score, for instance
      preferring a historical match that required fewer tokens to produce over an equally
      similar one that required more. This is particularly relevant when a TM lookup feeds a
      retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) translation workflow, where token cost and latency are
      part of what is being optimized.</para>
  </section>

  <para>Beyond translation-pair lookup, a concordance-style search, returning every stored entry
    whose <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;target&gt;</code> contains a given text
    fragment across every language present in the store, is a common complementary query mode.
    Either approach in this section can support it: an XPath <code>contains()</code> predicate
    for an XML-aware database, or a plain substring or full-text index alongside the vector index
    for a vector database. It is particularly useful for terminology review and quality checks
    that are not aimed at finding a reusable translation.</para>
</section>
