<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>Translation memory (TM) is a core technology of the localization industry. A TM stores
    previously translated content so that it can be retrieved and reused when equal or similar
    source content is encountered again, improving consistency and reducing translation effort
    and cost.</para>

  <para>Since 2005, the de facto standard for exchanging TM data between tools has been the
    Translation Memory eXchange (TMX) format [TMX 1.4b]. TMX was designed as a vendor-neutral
    interchange format, independent of any single authoring or extraction format. XLIFF, by
    contrast, is designed to carry bilingual (and, through packaging, multilingual) content
    through the localization process itself, from extraction through translation, review, and
    reintegration into the original format.</para>

  <para>As XLIFF adoption has grown, and as the XLIFF inline content model, segmentation model,
    and metadata modules have become richer, the gap between what an XLIFF document can
    represent and what TMX can represent has widened. Producing a TMX export of translated
    content, or importing TMX leverage into an XLIFF-based workflow, requires a conversion step.
    That conversion step is where information is put at risk.</para>

  <section id="tmxLimitations">
    <title>Limitations of TMX-Based Exchange</title>

    <para>TMX and XLIFF do not share an inline content model. TMX represents inline markup with
      a small, generic set of placeholder elements (<code>&lt;bpt&gt;</code>,
      <code>&lt;ept&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;it&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;ph&gt;</code>,
      <code>&lt;hi&gt;</code>) that carry no structural relationship to the original markup
      beyond matched pairing and free-form type/i attributes. XLIFF represents inline content
      with a richer, self-describing model (<code>&lt;pc&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;sc&gt;</code>,
      <code>&lt;ec&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;ph&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;mrk&gt;</code>,
      <code>&lt;sm&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;em&gt;</code>, backed by
      <code>&lt;originalData&gt;</code>). Converting XLIFF inline content into TMX inline
      content, and back again, is a lossy, implementation-specific mapping. There is no
      guarantee that a round trip through TMX preserves the original XLIFF markup, and in
      practice it frequently does not.</para>

    <para>TMX is defined by a Document Type Definition (DTD), not an XML Schema, and a TMX
      document is a self-contained top-level document with its own DOCTYPE. A TMX
      <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> cannot be embedded inside an XLIFF document, and an XLIFF
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> cannot be embedded inside a TMX document. The two formats can
      only be related to each other through external conversion, never through direct inclusion.
      This also means TMX content cannot participate in XLIFF's own extension and modularization
      mechanisms, such as the Translation Candidates module (<code>mtc:matches</code>, see
      [XLIFF-2.3-part2]), which is designed to hold XLIFF-native
      <code>&lt;source&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;target&gt;</code> pairs as leveraging matches inside
      a unit.</para>

    <para>Finally, a TMX file is a flat, unordered collection of <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code>
      elements. TMX defines no relationship between one translation unit and the next; any
      notion of document order, or of which segments originally appeared near each other, is
      lost once content is exported to TMX (short of ad hoc use of <code>&lt;prop&gt;</code> or
      <code>&lt;note&gt;</code> elements to reconstruct it). XLIFF does not have this
      limitation: an XLIFF document is structured as <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> containing one or
      more <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> elements, each containing one or more
      <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> elements, and that hierarchy is preserved in document order.
      Two segments that are adjacent in an XLIFF file are known to be adjacent in the source
      content, which is valuable context for TM leveraging, concordance search, and quality
      review that a flat TMX export cannot provide.</para>

    <para>For these reasons, this document recommends that plain XLIFF documents be used
      directly as the storage and interchange format for translation memory data, rather than
      converting content to and from TMX.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="changesFromPreviousVersion">
    <title>Changes From the Previous Version</title>

    <para>The list of changes from the previous version and any revision history can be found in
      Appendix 2.</para>
  </section>
</section>
