<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="safetySecurity">
  <title>Safety, Security, and Data Protection Considerations</title>

  <para>Translation memory content frequently originates from source documents that were never
    intended for public redistribution, and may contain personal data or confidential business
    information carried over from the original text. Storing that content as plain XLIFF,
    rather than as an opaque TM database, does not change its sensitivity; implementers should
    apply the same access controls, storage protections, and redistribution policies to
    XLIFF-based TM files and packages as they would to any other document containing the same
    source content.</para>

  <para>The Provenance module attributes described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml"
      targetptr="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for Translation Memory Entries</olink>,
    in particular <code>person</code>, can themselves constitute personal data about the
    translators and reviewers who worked on the content. Implementers should consider
    applicable data protection requirements (such as consent and retention limits) before
    populating, storing, or exchanging <code>person</code> values in translation memory data,
    and may omit <code>person</code> in favor of <code>agent</code>, <code>organization</code>,
    or <code>tool</code> where individual identification is not required.</para>

  <para>Translation memory exchange packages, as described in <olink targetdoc="exchange.xml"
      targetptr="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</olink>, are
    ordinary ZIP archives. Implementations that unpack them should apply the same precautions
    recommended for processing any untrusted ZIP archive, including validating that archive
    entries do not escape the intended extraction directory (path traversal) and guarding
    against archives crafted to consume excessive disk space or memory when decompressed.</para>
</section>
