<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd"[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="tmFormat">
  <title>XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</title>

  <para>This section describes the recommended approach for storing translation memory data as
    plain XLIFF documents, using XLIFF Core elements as they are already defined, without
    introducing a new TM-specific vocabulary.</para>

  <section id="designPrinciples">
    <title>Design Principles</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">No conversion.</emphasis> A TM entry is an XLIFF
          <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> containing one or more <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code>
          elements with <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;target&gt;</code> content,
          exactly as produced by any XLIFF-conformant extraction, translation, or review tool.
          Storing that content as translation memory requires no transformation of inline
          markup, and retrieving it for reuse in another XLIFF document requires no
          transformation back.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Full inline fidelity.</emphasis> Because TM entries remain
          XLIFF <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> elements, they retain the full XLIFF inline element
          model (<code>&lt;pc&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;sc&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;ec&gt;</code>,
          <code>&lt;ph&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;mrk&gt;</code>,
          <code>&lt;sm&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;em&gt;</code>) together with any associated
          <code>&lt;originalData&gt;</code>, instead of being reduced to the smaller TMX inline
          tag set.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Preserved order.</emphasis> Units and segments remain in
          the document order in which they were extracted, inside their originating
          <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> (and, where used, <code>&lt;group&gt;</code>). See <olink
            targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="structuralOrder">Structural Order and Segment
            Context</olink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Extensibility through existing modules.</emphasis> Any
          XLIFF module that can annotate a <code>&lt;file&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code>,
          or <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> in a normal XLIFF document, such as metadata, notes,
          size and length restriction, or the Provenance module described in <olink
            targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for
            Translation Memory Entries</olink>, applies equally when that document is used as a
          TM store. No parallel metadata model is required.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="harvesting">
    <title>Harvesting Translation Memory Entries</title>

    <para>A translation memory store, as described in this document, is not authored directly.
      It is populated by harvesting completed translation work out of ordinary XLIFF documents
      produced by an extraction, translation, and review process, and copying the resulting
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> elements, unchanged, into the
      store.</para>

    <para>Only <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> elements whose <code>state</code> attribute [XLIFF-2.3-part2]
      is set to <code>final</code> SHOULD be harvested into a translation memory store by
      default. The <code>initial</code>, <code>translated</code>, and <code>reviewed</code>
      values of <code>state</code> represent work still in progress; storing a segment in one of
      those states as reusable translation memory risks propagating unreviewed or incomplete
      translations into unrelated future projects. A segment that carries no <code>state</code>
      attribute, which defaults to <code>initial</code>, is likewise not eligible for
      harvesting. An implementation MAY instead apply a configurable minimum state threshold, for
      example accepting both <code>reviewed</code> and <code>final</code> segments, provided the
      threshold it used is disclosed to whoever queries the resulting store.</para>

    <para>Because the same project file may be harvested more than once, for example after a
      partial re-export, an implementation SHOULD derive a stable identifier for each harvested
      entry from values that do not change between harvests, such as the enclosing
      <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> <code>id</code> (or <code>original</code> attribute), the
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> <code>id</code>, and the segment's position within the unit.
      Deriving entry identifiers this way keeps harvesting idempotent: re-harvesting an unchanged
      file does not create duplicate entries in the store.</para>

    <para>Because harvesting is a filter rather than a transformation, it does not conflict with
      the "No conversion" design principle in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml"
        targetptr="designPrinciples">Design Principles</olink>: a harvested entry keeps exactly
      the source, target, and inline content it had in the file it was extracted from. Metadata
      recording where and how an entry was harvested, such as the originating project or job and
      the date of harvest, is expressed using the Provenance module, described in <olink
        targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for
        Translation Memory Entries</olink>, rather than by any new attribute defined by this
      document.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="structuralOrder">
    <title>Structural Order and Segment Context</title>

    <para>TMX represents a translation memory as a flat, unordered collection of
      <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> elements. TMX defines no relationship between one translation
      unit and any other; the position of a <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> in a TMX file carries no
      meaning.</para>

    <para>An XLIFF document used as a TM store retains the <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> &gt;
      <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> &gt; <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> hierarchy defined by XLIFF
      Core. This hierarchy carries information that a flat TU list cannot:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Document order</emphasis> is preserved. Segments that were
          adjacent in the original content remain adjacent, which supports context-aware
          leveraging (for example, preferring a match whose neighboring segments also match)
          and concordance search that shows a hit in its original surrounding context.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Provenance of the source document</emphasis> is preserved.
          The enclosing <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> retains attributes such as
          <code>original</code>, and can carry <code>&lt;file&gt;</code>-level metadata, so
          that every stored <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> remains traceable to the document it came
          from.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Grouping</emphasis> is preserved. Where the source content
          used <code>&lt;group&gt;</code> to represent structural divisions (chapters, UI
          screens, table rows, and so on), those divisions remain available to a TM consumer,
          instead of being discarded at export time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Combining the last two properties lets a TM consumer recover an <emphasis>in-context
      exact match</emphasis>: a 100% text match whose neighboring segments and originating
      document, identified by the enclosing <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> element's
      <code>original</code> attribute, also match the segment currently being translated. Tools
      commonly treat such a match as more reliable than an exact match recovered from an
      unrelated document or context, and can apply it without requiring human review. A flat TMX
      export, lacking both an equivalent to <code>original</code> and any notion of adjacency,
      cannot make this distinction without falling back to ad hoc <code>&lt;prop&gt;</code>
      conventions.</para>

    <para>A translation memory consumer that only needs unordered TU-style lookup can still
      treat every <code>&lt;segment&gt;</code> in every <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code> of every
      <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> as an independent entry, exactly as it would treat entries in a
      TMX file. The XLIFF-based representation is a strict superset of that capability: it does
      not require order and context to be used, but it does not discard them either.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="provenanceMetadata">
    <title>Provenance Metadata for Translation Memory Entries</title>

    <para>Reuse decisions in a translation memory workflow are often qualified by information
      about the origin of a given entry: who or what produced or last modified it, when, using
      what tool, and why. TMX addresses this only partially, through the
      <code>creationid</code>, <code>creationdate</code>, <code>changeid</code>,
      <code>changedate</code>, and <code>&lt;prop&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;note&gt;</code>
      mechanisms defined for <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;tuv&gt;</code>.</para>

    <para>The XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module (<code>pvn:</code>, under development by the OASIS
      XLIFF TC, see the <code>xliff-23</code> provenance module in this repository) is designed
      to record equivalent, and richer, information directly on XLIFF Core elements, using the
      <code>&lt;pvn:provenance&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;pvn:change&gt;</code> elements and
      attributes such as <code>agent</code>, <code>person</code>, <code>organization</code>,
      <code>tool</code>, <code>timestamp</code>, <code>appliesTo</code>, and
      <code>intent</code>. Because a TM entry stored as described in this document is an
      ordinary XLIFF <code>&lt;unit&gt;</code>, it can carry <code>&lt;pvn:provenance&gt;</code>
      metadata exactly as any other XLIFF unit can.</para>

    <para>Provenance is particularly important for entries populated through the harvesting
      process described in <olink targetdoc="tmFormat.xml" targetptr="harvesting">Harvesting
        Translation Memory Entries</olink>. Because a store accumulates entries across many
      separate harvest events, drawn from unrelated projects and completed at different times,
      the <code>&lt;pvn:provenance&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;pvn:change&gt;</code> elements are
      the mechanism by which a stored entry remains traceable back to the project, job, or
      process that produced it and the date it was harvested, once it is no longer possible to
      infer that origin from the entry's position in the store alone.</para>

    <para>This gives a translation memory consumer the ability to query stored entries by their
      provenance, for example to prefer entries produced by a specific translator or reviewed
      by a specific organization, to exclude machine-translated entries that were never
      reviewed by a person, or to filter by the date a translation was performed. Since
      provenance metadata is expressed using XLIFF elements and attributes rather than
      free-text <code>&lt;prop&gt;</code> values, as TMX requires, it can be validated and
      queried using standard XML tooling.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tmFormatExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A single translated document only ever has one <code>&lt;file&gt;</code>, so nothing
      about it shows translation memory <emphasis>reuse</emphasis>. The following example
      instead shows a TM store: an XLIFF document aggregating entries extracted from two
      unrelated projects, translated five months apart. The second project reuses a sentence
      already translated for the first, which is exactly the situation a translation memory
      exists to detect and exploit. Because both projects remain inside a single XLIFF
      document, each entry stays traceable to the <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> (and therefore the
      project) it came from, in the order it was added to the store, which a flat TMX
      <code>&lt;tu&gt;</code> list cannot represent.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;xliff version="2.3" srcLang="en" trgLang="es"
       xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:document:2.3"
       xmlns:pvn="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:pvn:2.3"&gt;
  &lt;file id="f1" original="manual/chapter3.html"&gt;
    &lt;unit id="tm-0001"&gt;
      &lt;segment&gt;
        &lt;source&gt;Your annual tax certificate is now available for download.&lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;target&gt;Su certificado fiscal anual ya está disponible para descarga.&lt;/target&gt;
      &lt;/segment&gt;
    &lt;/unit&gt;
    &lt;unit id="tm-0002"&gt;
      &lt;pvn:provenance&gt;
        &lt;pvn:change agent="Acme MT" appliesTo="target" timestamp="2026-01-15T10:15:00.000Z"/&gt;
      &lt;/pvn:provenance&gt;
      &lt;segment&gt;
        &lt;source&gt;Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;target&gt;Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target&gt;
      &lt;/segment&gt;
    &lt;/unit&gt;
  &lt;/file&gt;
  &lt;file id="f2" original="app/ui-strings.json"&gt;
    &lt;unit id="tm-1001"&gt;
      &lt;pvn:provenance&gt;
        &lt;pvn:change agent="TM Reuse" appliesTo="target" timestamp="2026-06-30T09:02:00.000Z"
          intent="100% match reused from tm-0002 (manual/chapter3.html)."/&gt;
      &lt;/pvn:provenance&gt;
      &lt;segment&gt;
        &lt;source&gt;Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;target&gt;Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target&gt;
      &lt;/segment&gt;
    &lt;/unit&gt;
    &lt;unit id="tm-1002"&gt;
      &lt;segment&gt;
        &lt;source&gt;Your session will expire in five minutes.&lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;target&gt;Su sesión caducará en cinco minutos.&lt;/target&gt;
      &lt;/segment&gt;
    &lt;/unit&gt;
  &lt;/file&gt;
&lt;/xliff&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Because <code>tm-1001</code> and <code>tm-0002</code> share the same
      <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> text, a TM consumer can find the reuse with a plain text
      comparison across the store, exactly as it would across a flat TMX file, then attribute
      that reuse using the Provenance module's <code>intent</code> attribute instead of a
      free-text TMX <code>&lt;prop&gt;</code>. And because both entries remain inside
      <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> elements that retain their own <code>original</code> attribute,
      the store also records which project each translation came from and in what order it was
      added, something a TMX export of the same two projects would have discarded.</para>
  </section>
</section>
