<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en-US" status="Committee Note Draft 01">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>XLIFF Translation Memory Version 1.0</title>

    <productname class="trade">xliff-tm</productname>

    <productnumber>cnd01</productnumber>

    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-this-authoritative">[ link to authoritative version of the published document ]</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous-authoritative">[ link to authoritative version of the published document ]</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-latest-authoritative">[ link to authoritative version of the published document ]</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="committee"><ulink url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf">OASIS
        XLIFF TC</ulink></releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <othercredit role="chair">
        <honorific>Dr</honorific>
        <firstname>Lucía</firstname>
        <surname>Morado Vázquez</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink url="https://www.unige.ch/en/">University of Geneva</ulink></orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>lucia.morado@unige.ch</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>lucia.morado@unige.ch</email>
      </othercredit>
      <othercredit role="chair">
        <firstname>Yoshito</firstname>
        <surname>Umaoka</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Individual</orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>y.umaoka@gmail.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>y.umaoka@gmail.com</email>
      </othercredit>
      <othercredit role="secretary">
        <firstname>Rodolfo M.</firstname>
        <surname>Raya</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink url="https://maxprograms.com">Maxprograms</ulink></orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email>
      </othercredit>
      <editor>
        <firstname>Rodolfo M.</firstname>
        <surname>Raya</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink url="https://maxprograms.com">Maxprograms</ulink></orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email>
      </editor>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>8 July 2026</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2026</year>
      <holder>OASIS Open, Inc. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice role="related">
      <title>Related Work</title>

      <para>This document replaces or supersedes:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>[ The full reference to the related document in IEEE reference format ]</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This document is related to:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="strong">[XLIFF-2.3-part2]</emphasis> XLIFF Version 2.3 Part 2:
            Extended. Edited by Rodolfo M. Raya and Lucía Morado Vázquez 8 July 2026. OASIS
            Committee Specification Draft 01. <ulink url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.3/xliff-v2.3-part2-extended.html">https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.3/xliff-v2.3-part2-extended.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="strong">[TMX 1.4b]</emphasis> Translation Memory eXchange (TMX)
            Version 1.4b. Edited by Yves Savourel. OSCAR Recommendation, 26 April 2005. <ulink url="https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This Committee Note describes an XLIFF-native approach for the representation and
        exchange of translation memory data, using plain XLIFF <code>&lt;file></code>,
        <code>&lt;unit></code>, and <code>&lt;segment></code> elements as the translation
        memory store itself, in place of the Translation Memory eXchange (TMX) format. The
        approach preserves the structure and semantics of XLIFF content, including bilingual
        text, inline elements, segmentation, and associated metadata, without the information
        loss that results from converting content to and from TMX's inline tag model. It also
        preserves the document order and structural relationship between translation units,
        file, unit, and segment, that TMX's flat, unordered list of translation units does not
        represent, and it allows richer metadata, such as provenance information, to be attached
        directly using existing XLIFF modules.</para>

      <para>This Committee Note also addresses the exchange of translation memory data for
        multilingual use. Because XLIFF documents are fundamentally bilingual, the Note
        recommends a packaging approach in which multiple related bilingual XLIFF files are
        distributed together in a single ZIP package with a manifest that identifies the
        relationships among them.</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice role="citation">
      <title>Citation format</title>
      <para>When referencing this document, the following citation format should be used:</para>
      <para>[ The full reference for this document in IEEE reference format ]</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice role="notices">
      <title>License, Document Status, and Notices</title>

      <para>Copyright © OASIS Open 2026. All Rights Reserved. For license and copyright
        information, and complete status, please see Annex A which contains the License,
        Document Status and Notices.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="scope">
  <title>Scope</title>

  <para>This Committee Note describes an XLIFF-native approach for storing and exchanging
    translation memory (TM) data, using plain XLIFF 2.x documents in place of the Translation
    Memory eXchange (TMX) format.</para>

  <para>Rather than defining a new container or converting bilingual content into a separate
    TM-specific format, this document recommends that XLIFF <code>&lt;file></code>,
    <code>&lt;unit></code>, and <code>&lt;segment></code> elements be used directly to hold
    translation units for later reuse. This preserves the full XLIFF inline element model,
    avoiding the loss of information that results from converting XLIFF inline markup to and
    from the TMX inline tag model, and preserves the structural order of content, which TMX's
    flat, unordered list of <code>&lt;tu></code> elements does not represent.</para>

  <para>This document also describes how the XLIFF Provenance module, under development for
    XLIFF 2.3, can be used to record and later query information about the origin of stored
    translation units, such as the agent, tool, or process that produced or modified them.</para>

  <para>Because a single XLIFF document is inherently bilingual, this document further describes
    a packaging convention for exchanging translation memory data across more than two
    languages, based on a set of related bilingual XLIFF files distributed together with a
    manifest.</para>
</section>
  <section id="definitionsAndAcronyms">
  <title>Definitions and Acronyms</title>

  <section id="definitions">
    <title>Definitions</title>

    <section id="termsDefinedElsewhere">
      <title>Terms Defined Elsewhere</title>

      <para>This document uses the following terms defined elsewhere:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Unit [XLIFF-2.3-part2]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>"A <code>&lt;unit></code> MAY contain both source and target content,
              allowing bilingual data to be stored."</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Segment [XLIFF-2.3-part2]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <code>&lt;segment></code> element, used to represent the smallest unit
              of translatable content addressed for translation, review, or other
              processing.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Provenance information [Provenance module, XLIFF 2.3, informative]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Information about the nature and origin of the localization data or
              process.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section id="termsDefinedInThisDocument">
      <title>Terms Defined in this Document</title>

      <para>This document defines the following terms:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation memory (TM)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A collection of previously translated source and target content, organized
              for retrieval and reuse when equal or similar source content is encountered
              again.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation memory entry</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A single stored source/target pair available for reuse, represented in this
              document as an XLIFF <code>&lt;unit></code> (or, where segmented,
              <code>&lt;segment></code>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation memory exchange package</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A ZIP archive containing one or more bilingual XLIFF files together with a
              manifest, used to exchange translation memory data across more than two
              languages, as described in <link linkend="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="abbreviationsAndAcronyms">
    <title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>

    <para>This document uses the following abbreviations and acronyms:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>TC: Technical Committee</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TM: Translation Memory</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TMX: Translation Memory eXchange</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TU: Translation Unit</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TUV: Translation Unit Variant (TMX)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>XML: Extensible Markup Language</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>ZIP: A common archive file format</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="documentConventions">
  <title>Document Conventions</title>

  <section id="keyWords">
    <title>Key Words</title>

    <para>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
      NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in <link linkend="rfc2119">[RFC2119]</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="typographicalConventions">
    <title>Typographical Conventions</title>

    <para>XML element names are shown enclosed in angle brackets, for example
      <code>&lt;unit></code>. XML attribute names are shown in fixed-width type without
      brackets, for example <code>id</code>. XML namespace prefixes used in examples
      (<code>xlf:</code>, <code>mtc:</code>, <code>pvn:</code>) follow the conventions
      established in [XLIFF-2.3-part2] and the XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module. Example XML is shown
      in fenced code blocks and is illustrative; it is not necessarily complete or
      schema-valid.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>Translation memory (TM) is a core technology of the localization industry. A TM stores
    previously translated content so that it can be retrieved and reused when equal or similar
    source content is encountered again, improving consistency and reducing translation effort
    and cost.</para>

  <para>Since 2005, the de facto standard for exchanging TM data between tools has been the
    Translation Memory eXchange (TMX) format [TMX 1.4b]. TMX was designed as a vendor-neutral
    interchange format, independent of any single authoring or extraction format. XLIFF, by
    contrast, is designed to carry bilingual (and, through packaging, multilingual) content
    through the localization process itself, from extraction through translation, review, and
    reintegration into the original format.</para>

  <para>As XLIFF adoption has grown, and as the XLIFF inline content model, segmentation model,
    and metadata modules have become richer, the gap between what an XLIFF document can
    represent and what TMX can represent has widened. Producing a TMX export of translated
    content, or importing TMX leverage into an XLIFF-based workflow, requires a conversion step.
    That conversion step is where information is put at risk.</para>

  <section id="tmxLimitations">
    <title>Limitations of TMX-Based Exchange</title>

    <para>TMX and XLIFF do not share an inline content model. TMX represents inline markup with
      a small, generic set of placeholder elements (<code>&lt;bpt></code>,
      <code>&lt;ept></code>, <code>&lt;it></code>, <code>&lt;ph></code>,
      <code>&lt;hi></code>) that carry no structural relationship to the original markup
      beyond matched pairing and free-form type/i attributes. XLIFF represents inline content
      with a richer, self-describing model (<code>&lt;pc></code>, <code>&lt;sc></code>,
      <code>&lt;ec></code>, <code>&lt;ph></code>, <code>&lt;mrk></code>,
      <code>&lt;sm></code>/<code>&lt;em></code>, backed by
      <code>&lt;originalData></code>). Converting XLIFF inline content into TMX inline
      content, and back again, is a lossy, implementation-specific mapping. There is no
      guarantee that a round trip through TMX preserves the original XLIFF markup, and in
      practice it frequently does not.</para>

    <para>TMX is defined by a Document Type Definition (DTD), not an XML Schema, and a TMX
      document is a self-contained top-level document with its own DOCTYPE. A TMX
      <code>&lt;tu></code> cannot be embedded inside an XLIFF document, and an XLIFF
      <code>&lt;unit></code> cannot be embedded inside a TMX document. The two formats can
      only be related to each other through external conversion, never through direct inclusion.
      This also means TMX content cannot participate in XLIFF's own extension and modularization
      mechanisms, such as the Translation Candidates module (<code>mtc:matches</code>, see
      [XLIFF-2.3-part2]), which is designed to hold XLIFF-native
      <code>&lt;source></code>/<code>&lt;target></code> pairs as leveraging matches inside
      a unit.</para>

    <para>Finally, a TMX file is a flat, unordered collection of <code>&lt;tu></code>
      elements. TMX defines no relationship between one translation unit and the next; any
      notion of document order, or of which segments originally appeared near each other, is
      lost once content is exported to TMX (short of ad hoc use of <code>&lt;prop></code> or
      <code>&lt;note></code> elements to reconstruct it). XLIFF does not have this
      limitation: an XLIFF document is structured as <code>&lt;file></code> containing one or
      more <code>&lt;unit></code> elements, each containing one or more
      <code>&lt;segment></code> elements, and that hierarchy is preserved in document order.
      Two segments that are adjacent in an XLIFF file are known to be adjacent in the source
      content, which is valuable context for TM leveraging, concordance search, and quality
      review that a flat TMX export cannot provide. This is the same context that CAT tools rely
      on to identify an in-context exact match (ICE), sometimes marketed as a "101% match": a
      100% text match that also occurred in the same position, in the same source document, as
      the segment currently being translated. Because TMX carries no structural relationship
      between one <code>&lt;tu></code> and the next, tools that offer ICE matching against TMX
      data have to reconstruct that adjacency after the fact, typically through vendor-specific
      heuristics or ad hoc <code>&lt;prop></code> conventions. Because the XLIFF-native store
      described in this document preserves both the enclosing <code>&lt;file></code> and
      document order directly, as described in <link linkend="structuralOrder">Structural Order and Segment Context</link>, identifying an
      in-context exact match is a native capability of the store rather than a heuristic
      reconstruction.</para>

    <para>For these reasons, this document recommends that plain XLIFF documents be used
      directly as the storage and interchange format for translation memory data, rather than
      converting content to and from TMX.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="changesFromPreviousVersion">
    <title>Changes From the Previous Version</title>

    <para>The list of changes from the previous version and any revision history can be found in
      Appendix 2.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="tmFormat">
  <title>XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</title>

  <para>This section describes the recommended approach for storing translation memory data as
    plain XLIFF documents, using XLIFF Core elements as they are already defined, without
    introducing a new TM-specific vocabulary.</para>

  <section id="designPrinciples">
    <title>Design Principles</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">No conversion.</emphasis> A TM entry is an XLIFF
          <code>&lt;unit></code> containing one or more <code>&lt;segment></code>
          elements with <code>&lt;source></code> and <code>&lt;target></code> content,
          exactly as produced by any XLIFF-conformant extraction, translation, or review tool.
          Storing that content as translation memory requires no transformation of inline
          markup, and retrieving it for reuse in another XLIFF document requires no
          transformation back.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Full inline fidelity.</emphasis> Because TM entries remain
          XLIFF <code>&lt;unit></code> elements, they retain the full XLIFF inline element
          model (<code>&lt;pc></code>, <code>&lt;sc></code>/<code>&lt;ec></code>,
          <code>&lt;ph></code>, <code>&lt;mrk></code>,
          <code>&lt;sm></code>/<code>&lt;em></code>) together with any associated
          <code>&lt;originalData></code>, instead of being reduced to the smaller TMX inline
          tag set.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Preserved order.</emphasis> Units and segments remain in
          the document order in which they were extracted, inside their originating
          <code>&lt;file></code> (and, where used, <code>&lt;group></code>). See <link linkend="structuralOrder">Structural Order and Segment            Context</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Extensibility through existing modules.</emphasis> Any
          XLIFF module that can annotate a <code>&lt;file></code>, <code>&lt;unit></code>,
          or <code>&lt;segment></code> in a normal XLIFF document, such as metadata, notes,
          size and length restriction, the Provenance module described in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for            Translation Memory Entries</link>, or the Glossary module described in <link linkend="glossaryTerminology">Glossary Terminology on            Harvested Units</link>, applies equally when that document is used as a TM store.
          No parallel metadata model is required.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="harvesting">
    <title>Harvesting Translation Memory Entries</title>

    <para>A translation memory store, as described in this document, is not authored directly.
      It is populated by harvesting completed translation work out of ordinary XLIFF documents
      produced by an extraction, translation, and review process, and copying the resulting
      <code>&lt;unit></code> and <code>&lt;segment></code> elements, unchanged, into the
      store.</para>

    <para>Only <code>&lt;segment></code> elements whose <code>state</code> attribute [XLIFF-2.3-part2]
      is set to <code>final</code> SHOULD be harvested into a translation memory store by
      default. The <code>initial</code>, <code>translated</code>, and <code>reviewed</code>
      values of <code>state</code> represent work still in progress; storing a segment in one of
      those states as reusable translation memory risks propagating unreviewed or incomplete
      translations into unrelated future projects. A segment that carries no <code>state</code>
      attribute, which defaults to <code>initial</code>, is likewise not eligible for
      harvesting. An implementation MAY instead apply a configurable minimum state threshold, for
      example accepting both <code>reviewed</code> and <code>final</code> segments, provided the
      threshold it used is disclosed to whoever queries the resulting store.</para>

    <para>Because the same project file may be harvested more than once, for example after a
      partial re-export, an implementation SHOULD derive a stable identifier for each harvested
      entry from values that do not change between harvests, such as the enclosing
      <code>&lt;file></code> <code>id</code> (or <code>original</code> attribute), the
      <code>&lt;unit></code> <code>id</code>, and the segment's position within the unit.
      Deriving entry identifiers this way keeps harvesting idempotent: re-harvesting an unchanged
      file does not create duplicate entries in the store.</para>

    <para>Because harvesting is a filter rather than a transformation, it does not conflict with
      the "No conversion" design principle in <link linkend="designPrinciples">Design Principles</link>: a harvested entry keeps exactly
      the source, target, and inline content it had in the file it was extracted from. Metadata
      recording where and how an entry was harvested, such as the originating project or job and
      the date of harvest, is expressed using the Provenance module, described in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for        Translation Memory Entries</link>, rather than by any new attribute defined by this
      document.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="structuralOrder">
    <title>Structural Order and Segment Context</title>

    <para>TMX represents a translation memory as a flat, unordered collection of
      <code>&lt;tu></code> elements. TMX defines no relationship between one translation
      unit and any other; the position of a <code>&lt;tu></code> in a TMX file carries no
      meaning.</para>

    <para>An XLIFF document used as a TM store retains the <code>&lt;file></code> >
      <code>&lt;unit></code> > <code>&lt;segment></code> hierarchy defined by XLIFF
      Core. This hierarchy carries information that a flat TU list cannot:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Document order</emphasis> is preserved. Segments that were
          adjacent in the original content remain adjacent, which supports context-aware
          leveraging (for example, preferring a match whose neighboring segments also match)
          and concordance search that shows a hit in its original surrounding context.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Provenance of the source document</emphasis> is preserved.
          The enclosing <code>&lt;file></code> retains attributes such as
          <code>original</code>, and can carry <code>&lt;file></code>-level metadata, so
          that every stored <code>&lt;unit></code> remains traceable to the document it came
          from.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Grouping</emphasis> is preserved. Where the source content
          used <code>&lt;group></code> to represent structural divisions (chapters, UI
          screens, table rows, and so on), those divisions remain available to a TM consumer,
          instead of being discarded at export time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Combining the last two properties lets a TM consumer recover an <emphasis>in-context
      exact match</emphasis>: a 100% text match whose neighboring segments and originating
      document, identified by the enclosing <code>&lt;file></code> element's
      <code>original</code> attribute, also match the segment currently being translated. Tools
      commonly treat such a match as more reliable than an exact match recovered from an
      unrelated document or context, and can apply it without requiring human review. A flat TMX
      export, lacking both an equivalent to <code>original</code> and any notion of adjacency,
      cannot make this distinction without falling back to ad hoc <code>&lt;prop></code>
      conventions.</para>

    <para>A translation memory consumer that only needs unordered TU-style lookup can still
      treat every <code>&lt;segment></code> in every <code>&lt;unit></code> of every
      <code>&lt;file></code> as an independent entry, exactly as it would treat entries in a
      TMX file. The XLIFF-based representation is a strict superset of that capability: it does
      not require order and context to be used, but it does not discard them either.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="provenanceMetadata">
    <title>Provenance Metadata for Translation Memory Entries</title>

    <para>Reuse decisions in a translation memory workflow are often qualified by information
      about the origin of a given entry: who or what produced or last modified it, when, using
      what tool, and why. TMX addresses this only partially, through the
      <code>creationid</code>, <code>creationdate</code>, <code>changeid</code>,
      <code>changedate</code>, and <code>&lt;prop></code>/<code>&lt;note></code>
      mechanisms defined for <code>&lt;tu></code> and <code>&lt;tuv></code>.</para>

    <para>The XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module (<code>pvn:</code>, under development by the OASIS
      XLIFF TC, see the <code>xliff-23</code> provenance module in this repository) is designed
      to record equivalent, and richer, information directly on XLIFF Core elements, using the
      <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> and <code>&lt;pvn:change></code> elements and
      attributes such as <code>agent</code>, <code>person</code>, <code>organization</code>,
      <code>tool</code>, <code>timestamp</code>, <code>appliesTo</code>, and
      <code>intent</code>. Because a TM entry stored as described in this document is an
      ordinary XLIFF <code>&lt;unit></code>, it can carry <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code>
      metadata exactly as any other XLIFF unit can.</para>

    <para>Provenance is particularly important for entries populated through the harvesting
      process described in <link linkend="harvesting">Harvesting        Translation Memory Entries</link>. Because a store accumulates entries across many
      separate harvest events, drawn from unrelated projects and completed at different times,
      the <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> and <code>&lt;pvn:change></code> elements are
      the mechanism by which a stored entry remains traceable back to the project, job, or
      process that produced it and the date it was harvested, once it is no longer possible to
      infer that origin from the entry's position in the store alone.</para>

    <para>This gives a translation memory consumer the ability to query stored entries by their
      provenance, for example to prefer entries produced by a specific translator or reviewed
      by a specific organization, to exclude machine-translated entries that were never
      reviewed by a person, or to filter by the date a translation was performed. Since
      provenance metadata is expressed using XLIFF elements and attributes rather than
      free-text <code>&lt;prop></code> values, as TMX requires, it can be validated and
      queried using standard XML tooling.</para>

    <para>A segment is frequently the product of more than one processing step, for example an
      initial machine translation, one or more revisions, and a final human verification, and
      <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> can hold that entire chain as successive
      <code>&lt;pvn:change></code> elements, not only the most recent one. When an XLIFF
      document is harvested into a TM store, as described in <link linkend="harvesting">Harvesting Translation Memory Entries</link>, the harvesting
      agent SHOULD preserve the complete <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> element associated
      with the harvested unit or segment, rather than collapsing it to a summary of the current
      state. Preserving the full chain lets a TM consumer evaluate the lineage of a translation:
      for example, a consumer can filter a search to entries whose chain includes a
      <code>&lt;pvn:change></code> with a <code>person</code> attribute, to prefer or require
      translations that received human review at some point, even if the most recent change in
      the chain was machine-generated.</para>

    <para>The following excerpt shows a segment that went through exactly such a chain: a first
      pass by a machine translation agent, recorded together with the token cost of producing it
      using the <code>&lt;pvn:usage></code> element, followed by a human revision recorded
      with an explanatory <code>intent</code>:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;unit id="tm-0098" xmlns:pvn="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:pvn:2.3">
  &lt;pvn:provenance>
    &lt;pvn:change agent="Acme MT" appliesTo="target" timestamp="2026-07-10T10:00:00.000Z">
      &lt;pvn:usage usageUnit="token">24&lt;/pvn:usage>
      &lt;pvn:value>Su certificado anual de impuestos ya está listo para descargar.&lt;/pvn:value>
    &lt;/pvn:change>
    &lt;pvn:change person="Reviewer A" tool="Example CAT Tool" appliesTo="target"
      timestamp="2026-07-10T10:15:00.000Z"
      intent="Changed 'listo' to 'disponible' to match corporate terminology.">
      &lt;pvn:value>Su certificado anual de impuestos ya está disponible para descargar.&lt;/pvn:value>
    &lt;/pvn:change>
  &lt;/pvn:provenance>
  &lt;segment>
    &lt;source>Your annual tax certificate is now available for download.&lt;/source>
    &lt;target>Su certificado anual de impuestos ya está disponible para descargar.&lt;/target>
  &lt;/segment>
&lt;/unit></programlisting>

    <para>A consumer that only inspects the current <code>&lt;target></code> sees a finished
      translation with no indication of how it was produced. A consumer that reads the full
      <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> chain can instead tell that the entry was
      machine-translated and then human-reviewed, and could equally well have told the reverse,
      or that no human ever touched it, had the chain been different.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="glossaryTerminology">
    <title>Glossary Terminology on Harvested Units</title>

    <para>XLIFF 2.x defines a Glossary module (<code>gls:</code>) that lets a
      <code>&lt;unit></code> carry a <code>&lt;gls:glossary></code> element containing one
      or more <code>&lt;gls:glossEntry></code> elements, each recording a source-language
      <code>&lt;gls:term></code>, its approved target-language
      <code>&lt;gls:translation></code>, and an optional <code>&lt;gls:definition></code>.
      Because harvesting a unit into a TM store, as described in <link linkend="harvesting">Harvesting Translation Memory Entries</link>, copies its content
      unchanged, any <code>&lt;gls:glossary></code> annotation already present on a source
      unit is preserved automatically: no special handling is required to retain it, and none is
      possible to accidentally lose, since harvesting a unit means copying the whole unit.</para>

    <para>This turns a store built from terminology-annotated projects into more than a
      collection of reusable translations: it is also a terminology reference. A TM consumer
      that finds a match can inspect the matched unit's <code>&lt;gls:glossary></code>
      element to see which terms that translation was required to use, and how they were
      rendered, without maintaining a separate glossary system alongside the store. The same
      content is also available to whichever retrieval mechanism is used, as described in <link linkend="implementation">Creating and Searching a        Translation Memory Store</link>: an XML-aware database can query on
      <code>&lt;gls:term></code> text directly, and a vector database can index it alongside
      the segment's source and target text.</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;unit id="tm-0002">
  &lt;gls:glossary xmlns:gls="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:glossary:2.0">
    &lt;gls:glossEntry>
      &lt;gls:term>fiscal year&lt;/gls:term>
      &lt;gls:translation>año fiscal&lt;/gls:translation>
    &lt;/gls:glossEntry>
  &lt;/gls:glossary>
  &lt;segment>
    &lt;source>Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source>
    &lt;target>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target>
  &lt;/segment>
&lt;/unit></programlisting>

    <para>A future TM lookup that matches this unit's source text now also surfaces the approved
      term mapping for "fiscal year," letting a consumer enforce the same terminology choice
      instead of only reusing the sentence-level translation.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tmFormatExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A single translated document only ever has one <code>&lt;file></code>, so nothing
      about it shows translation memory <emphasis>reuse</emphasis>. The following example
      instead shows a TM store: an XLIFF document aggregating entries extracted from two
      unrelated projects, translated five months apart. The second project reuses a sentence
      already translated for the first, which is exactly the situation a translation memory
      exists to detect and exploit. Because both projects remain inside a single XLIFF
      document, each entry stays traceable to the <code>&lt;file></code> (and therefore the
      project) it came from, in the order it was added to the store, which a flat TMX
      <code>&lt;tu></code> list cannot represent.</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;xliff version="2.3" srcLang="en" trgLang="es"
       xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:document:2.3"
       xmlns:pvn="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:pvn:2.3">
  &lt;file id="f1" original="manual/chapter3.html">
    &lt;unit id="tm-0001">
      &lt;segment>
        &lt;source>Your annual tax certificate is now available for download.&lt;/source>
        &lt;target>Su certificado fiscal anual ya está disponible para descarga.&lt;/target>
      &lt;/segment>
    &lt;/unit>
    &lt;unit id="tm-0002">
      &lt;pvn:provenance>
        &lt;pvn:change agent="Acme MT" appliesTo="target" timestamp="2026-01-15T10:15:00.000Z">
          &lt;pvn:value>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/pvn:value>
        &lt;/pvn:change>
      &lt;/pvn:provenance>
      &lt;segment>
        &lt;source>Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source>
        &lt;target>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target>
      &lt;/segment>
    &lt;/unit>
  &lt;/file>
  &lt;file id="f2" original="app/ui-strings.json">
    &lt;unit id="tm-1001">
      &lt;pvn:provenance>
        &lt;pvn:change agent="TM Reuse" appliesTo="target" timestamp="2026-06-30T09:02:00.000Z"
          intent="100% match reused from tm-0002 (manual/chapter3.html).">
          &lt;pvn:value>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/pvn:value>
        &lt;/pvn:change>
      &lt;/pvn:provenance>
      &lt;segment>
        &lt;source>Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source>
        &lt;target>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target>
      &lt;/segment>
    &lt;/unit>
    &lt;unit id="tm-1002">
      &lt;segment>
        &lt;source>Your session will expire in five minutes.&lt;/source>
        &lt;target>Su sesión caducará en cinco minutos.&lt;/target>
      &lt;/segment>
    &lt;/unit>
  &lt;/file>
&lt;/xliff></programlisting>

    <para>Because <code>tm-1001</code> and <code>tm-0002</code> share the same
      <code>&lt;source></code> text, a TM consumer can find the reuse with a plain text
      comparison across the store, exactly as it would across a flat TMX file, then attribute
      that reuse using the Provenance module's <code>intent</code> attribute instead of a
      free-text TMX <code>&lt;prop></code>. And because both entries remain inside
      <code>&lt;file></code> elements that retain their own <code>original</code> attribute,
      the store also records which project each translation came from and in what order it was
      added, something a TMX export of the same two projects would have discarded.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="exchange">
  <title>Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</title>

  <para>An XLIFF document is bilingual: it declares a single <code>srcLang</code> and a single
    <code>trgLang</code>. A translation memory, however, is often required to hold or exchange
    content across more than two languages. TMX addresses this within a single file, because a
    <code>&lt;tu></code> can hold any number of <code>&lt;tuv></code> elements, one per
    language.</para>

  <para>This document recommends addressing the same requirement not by making an individual
    XLIFF document multilingual, which would be a departure from the XLIFF Core data model, but
    by packaging multiple bilingual XLIFF files together, one per source/target language pair,
    along with a manifest that identifies the relationship among them. This keeps every
    individual file fully conformant with, and processable by, any existing XLIFF 2.x tool,
    while still allowing a translation memory covering many languages to be exchanged as a
    single unit.</para>

  <para>A multilingual translation memory is rarely built from a single source language: it
    typically accumulates from projects extracted from whatever source language each originating
    document happened to use. Accordingly, the files in a package are not required to share a
    common <code>srcLang</code>. A single package MAY combine bilingual files representing any
    number of independent source/target language pairs, for example an
    <code>en-es.xlf</code> file alongside an unrelated <code>fr-de.xlf</code> file, with the
    manifest simply recording the <code>srcLang</code> and <code>trgLang</code> that each file
    declares.</para>

  <section id="packageStructure">
    <title>Package Structure</title>

    <para>A translation memory exchange package is a ZIP archive (as defined in [ZIP APPNOTE])
      with the following content:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more bilingual XLIFF files, each conforming to [XLIFF-2.3-part2] or later,
          each independently declaring its own <code>srcLang</code> and <code>trgLang</code>.
          Files in the same package are not required to share a common
          <code>srcLang</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A single manifest file, described in <link linkend="manifestFile">Manifest File</link>, that groups the XLIFF files in the
          package into one or more aligned sets by shared source language and records the
          language pair each file represents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The XLIFF files in a package are not required to sit at the root of the archive. They
      MAY instead be organized into any folder structure the package author finds convenient, for
      example one folder per language pair. The manifest's <code>href</code> value for each file
      gives that file's actual path within the package, so a consumer locates every file through
      the manifest rather than by assuming a particular layout.</para>

    <para>Every file listed in the manifest belongs to exactly one aligned set: a group of files
      that share a common <code>srcLang</code> and were extracted from the same source content.
      A file with no counterpart sharing its source is simply the only member of its own aligned
      set. Corresponding translation units across the files in an aligned set MUST use the same
      <code>&lt;unit></code> <code>id</code> value (and, where segmented, the same
      <code>&lt;segment></code> <code>id</code> value). This is what lets a consumer treat
      aligned-set membership as a guarantee rather than a hint: a match against a given
      <code>&lt;unit></code> <code>id</code> in one file of the set is known to correspond to
      the same source context in every other file of the set, which lets a tool synthesize a
      multi-target match across every language in the set directly from a single-language
      lookup, without re-querying each file separately. This mirrors, at the package level, the
      alignment that a multilingual <code>&lt;tu></code> provides in a single TMX file, while
      extending it to packages whose source language differs from one aligned set to the
      next.</para>

    <para>A tool that does not support this manifest format is not prevented from using the
      package. Because every file it lists remains an independent, fully conformant XLIFF
      document, such a tool MAY simply extract the archive, ignore <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code>,
      and ingest each bilingual XLIFF file on its own, exactly as it would ingest any other XLIFF
      file it was given individually. The manifest adds cross-file structure for tools that
      understand it; it is not required to make the package's contents usable.</para>

    <para>The same fallback applies if a ZIP archive of bilingual XLIFF files has no
      <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code> at all: such an archive does not conform to this document
      as a Translation Memory Exchange Package, but a tool MAY still treat it as an unlinked
      collection of independent bilingual memories and ingest each file individually.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="manifestFile">
    <title>Manifest File</title>

    <para>The manifest is an XML file, named <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code>, placed at the root of
      the package. Its root <code>&lt;tmPackage></code> element MAY carry a
      <code>packageId</code> attribute identifying the package and a <code>created</code>
      attribute recording when it was assembled; both are informational and carry no processing
      requirement. It groups the package's XLIFF files into one or more
      <code>&lt;alignedSet></code> elements, each declaring the shared <code>srcLang</code> of
      its members and MAY carry a <code>&lt;description></code> child element with a
      human-readable summary of what the set represents. Within an aligned set, each file is
      listed as a <code>&lt;file></code> element giving the <code>href</code> path to the file
      within the package and the <code>trgLang</code> it represents, and MAY carry a
      <code>hash</code> attribute so a consumer can verify the file was not corrupted or altered
      in transit.</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0"
    packageId="pkg-2026-finance-tm" created="2026-07-10T13:43:00Z">
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-01" srcLang="en">
    &lt;description>Financial terminology memory extracted from Q2 2026 projects.&lt;/description>
    &lt;file href="en-es.xlf" trgLang="es"
      hash="sha256:3451e18e0aa54c65398509e1decd963e1ea1fafa4dee37fde6b1e2585c0f74ec"/>
    &lt;file href="en-fr.xlf" trgLang="fr"
      hash="sha256:ec076145e71a8c08b9e78253ceac02bc9a0f98a56577216987ab6dea15e7b457"/>
  &lt;/alignedSet>
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-02" srcLang="fr">
    &lt;file href="fr-de.xlf" trgLang="de"
      hash="sha256:6dc9abf3aace245aefb08f4220e8355dc237de9ef289c60c87abd734ed552986"/>
  &lt;/alignedSet>
&lt;/tmPackage></programlisting>

    <para>A manifest is not required to declare the same <code>srcLang</code> for every aligned
      set it contains, as the example above illustrates: <code>en-es.xlf</code> and
      <code>en-fr.xlf</code> both originate from English source content and are grouped together
      in <code>set-01</code>, while <code>fr-de.xlf</code> is an unrelated bilingual file with
      French as its source language and forms the single-member <code>set-02</code> on its
      own.</para>

    <para>The <code>hash</code> attribute lets an exchanging tool make two decisions before it
      opens or parses a potentially large XLIFF file. When synchronizing against a package it
      has seen before, a tool can compare a file's <code>hash</code> value in the new manifest
      against the hash of the copy it already holds, and skip reparsing entirely when they
      match, rather than reparsing every file on every sync. After extracting a file from the
      archive, a tool can also recompute its hash and compare it against the value recorded in
      the manifest to detect truncation or corruption introduced during transport, before that
      file's content is allowed to reach a TM store.</para>

    <para>A <code>hash</code> value is expressed as <code>algorithm:digest</code>, where
      <code>algorithm</code> identifies the hash function used (<code>sha256</code> is
      RECOMMENDED) and <code>digest</code> is the lowercase hexadecimal digest it produces. Where
      a <code>&lt;file></code> entry carries a <code>hash</code> value, an exchanging tool
      SHOULD validate the extracted file's content against it before committing that content to
      a TM store, and SHOULD treat a mismatch as a sign of a corrupted or incomplete transfer
      rather than importing it. A matching hash only guards against accidental
      corruption in transport: because both a file and its manifest entry are typically produced
      by the same party, a hash alone does not protect against deliberate tampering by anyone
      able to modify the package.</para>

    <para><emphasis>The manifest namespace, element and attribute names, and XML Schema shown
      above are provisional and subject to review by the OASIS XLIFF TC before this Note
      advances beyond Committee Note Draft.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="exchangeExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A translation memory accumulated from an English-source project translated into
      Spanish and French, together with an unrelated project whose source was French and whose
      target was German, would be packaged as:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">tm-package.zip
├── xliff-manifest.xml
├── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr.xlf
└── fr-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>Each of <code>en-es.xlf</code>, <code>en-fr.xlf</code>, and <code>fr-de.xlf</code> is
      an ordinary bilingual XLIFF document as described in <link linkend="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</link>, and each can be
      consumed independently by a tool that only needs one language pair, or together by a tool
      that reads <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code> to reconstruct the full set. <code>en-es.xlf</code>
      and <code>en-fr.xlf</code> share a common source language and belong to the same aligned
      set, so they MUST be aligned by <code>&lt;unit></code> and <code>&lt;segment></code>
      <code>id</code> as described in <link linkend="packageStructure">Package Structure</link>; <code>fr-de.xlf</code> has no
      source language in common with the other two files and forms its own aligned set, outside
      that alignment.</para>

    <para>As described in <link linkend="packageStructure">Package        Structure</link>, the same three files MAY instead be organized into one folder per
      language pair:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">tm-package.zip
├── xliff-manifest.xml
├── en-es/
│   └── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr/
│   └── en-fr.xlf
└── fr-de/
    └── fr-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>with the manifest updated to match:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;tmPackage xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:tm-manifest:1.0" version="1.0"
    packageId="pkg-2026-finance-tm" created="2026-07-10T13:43:00Z">
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-01" srcLang="en">
    &lt;file href="en-es/en-es.xlf" trgLang="es"
      hash="sha256:3451e18e0aa54c65398509e1decd963e1ea1fafa4dee37fde6b1e2585c0f74ec"/>
    &lt;file href="en-fr/en-fr.xlf" trgLang="fr"
      hash="sha256:ec076145e71a8c08b9e78253ceac02bc9a0f98a56577216987ab6dea15e7b457"/>
  &lt;/alignedSet>
  &lt;alignedSet id="set-02" srcLang="fr">
    &lt;file href="fr-de/fr-de.xlf" trgLang="de"
      hash="sha256:6dc9abf3aace245aefb08f4220e8355dc237de9ef289c60c87abd734ed552986"/>
  &lt;/alignedSet>
&lt;/tmPackage></programlisting>

    <para>Both layouts are valid and equivalent: a conformant consumer resolves every file
      through the <code>href</code> value recorded in the manifest rather than by assuming
      either layout.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="implementation">
  <title>Creating and Searching a Translation Memory Store</title>

  <para>This section is informative and does not define conformance requirements. It describes
    practical, non-mandatory approaches for creating and querying a translation memory store as
    described in <link linkend="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation    Memory Format</link>. Implementers MAY use either of these approaches, a combination of
    them, or an approach not described here; this document does not mandate a particular storage
    or retrieval technology.</para>

  <para>The packaging convention described in <link linkend="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</link> is intended
    for exchanging translation memory data between parties and tools, not as an implementation
    architecture. An implementation is not expected to query a ZIP package directly: it typically
    loads the bilingual XLIFF files it receives, or the ones it produces by harvesting as
    described in <link linkend="harvesting">Harvesting Translation      Memory Entries</link>, into whichever storage and retrieval mechanism it uses internally,
    of which the following are two examples.</para>

  <note>
    <title>Fuzzy Search Versus Semantic Search</title>

    <para>The two approaches described in this section answer different questions. Fuzzy
      search, as provided by an XML-aware database (through XPath/XQuery string functions or a
      similarity extension) or by a SQL database (through trigram indexes, edit-distance
      functions, or full-text search), measures how similar two strings are as sequences of
      characters. It reliably finds near-duplicates that differ by a word, a typo, or a small
      edit, but has no notion of meaning: it can rank a sentence whose negation flips its meaning
      as a close match to the original, and it will not find a paraphrase that shares no wording
      at all.</para>

    <para>Semantic search, as provided by a vector database over text embeddings, measures how
      similar two passages are in meaning, independent of wording. It finds paraphrases that a
      fuzzy search misses, but is not guaranteed to penalize a small, meaning-changing edit as
      heavily as a fuzzy search would, since embeddings can place semantically related but
      contradictory statements close together in vector space. This complementary blind spot is
      why <link linkend="vectorDatabaseApproach">Vector        Database and Similarity Search</link> recommends blending a semantic score with a fuzzy
      score rather than relying on either alone.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Organizations with an existing SQL-based translation memory engine, many of which
    already parse a source/target pair out of a TMX <code>&lt;tu></code>/<code>&lt;tuv></code>
    and store it in relational tables, do not need to replace that engine to work with a store
    described in this document: the same import step can instead read
    <code>&lt;source></code>/<code>&lt;target></code> content directly out of XLIFF
    <code>&lt;segment></code> elements. This is a low-effort migration path that reuses
    existing search and scoring logic, but on its own it does not bring the context-aware
    retrieval described in <link linkend="xmlDatabaseApproach">XML-Aware Database and XPath Retrieval</link> or the
    paraphrase-level retrieval described in <link linkend="vectorDatabaseApproach">Vector Database and Similarity Search</link>: a
    relational schema built around a flat source/target pair typically discards the same
    document order, <code>&lt;file></code> origin, and grouping that a flat TMX export
    discards, unless the importer is extended to capture them as additional columns.</para>

  <section id="xmlDatabaseApproach">
    <title>XML-Aware Database and XPath Retrieval</title>

    <para>Because a translation memory store described in this document is plain, well-formed
      XLIFF, it can be loaded directly into an XML-aware database and queried with XPath or
      XQuery, without any transformation of its content. A query can match on
      <code>&lt;source></code> text, restrict candidates to a particular
      <code>&lt;file></code> <code>original</code> value or Provenance attribute as described
      in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for        Translation Memory Entries</link>, or exploit the preserved document order described in
      <link linkend="structuralOrder">Structural Order and Segment        Context</link> to retrieve a match together with its neighboring segments.</para>

    <para>Examples of XML-aware databases that support this style of storage and query include,
      without limitation, BaseX, eXist-db, MarkLogic, and Oracle XML DB. Naming these products is
      illustrative only and does not constitute an endorsement or a requirement to use any of
      them.</para>

    <para>For example, the following excerpt of a translation memory store, taken from the store
      shown in <link linkend="tmFormatExample">Example</link>,
      contains two entries with identical source text, harvested from two different
      documents:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;file id="f1" original="manual/chapter3.html">
  &lt;unit id="tm-0002">
    &lt;segment>
      &lt;source>Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source>
      &lt;target>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target>
    &lt;/segment>
  &lt;/unit>
&lt;/file>
&lt;file id="f2" original="app/ui-strings.json">
  &lt;unit id="tm-1001">
    &lt;segment>
      &lt;source>Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.&lt;/source>
      &lt;target>Descargue su certificado antes de que finalice el año fiscal.&lt;/target>
    &lt;/segment>
  &lt;/unit>
&lt;/file></programlisting>

    <para>An XPath query that matches on source text alone:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">//unit[segment/source = 'Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.']</programlisting>

    <para>returns both <code>tm-0002</code> and <code>tm-1001</code>, since both segments share
      the same exact source text. If the unit currently being translated originated from
      <code>manual/chapter3.html</code>, the query can be narrowed to prefer an in-context exact
      match, as described in <link linkend="structuralOrder">Structural        Order and Segment Context</link>, by also constraining the enclosing
      <code>&lt;file></code> element's <code>original</code> attribute:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">//file[@original = 'manual/chapter3.html']
    /unit[segment/source = 'Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year.']</programlisting>

    <para>which returns only <code>tm-0002</code>, the entry harvested from the same document as
      the unit being translated.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="vectorDatabaseApproach">
    <title>Vector Database and Similarity Search</title>

    <para>Alternatively, the <code>&lt;source></code> (and, where useful,
      <code>&lt;target></code>) text of each harvested <code>&lt;segment></code> can be
      converted to a numeric embedding by a text embedding model and indexed in a vector
      database, with each vector referencing the <code>&lt;unit></code> and
      <code>&lt;file></code> it was derived from. Retrieval is then performed as a similarity
      search over embeddings rather than an exact or XPath-based text match, which can surface
      fuzzy matches that share meaning but not exact wording. As with the XML-database approach,
      the enclosing <code>&lt;file></code> <code>original</code> attribute and Provenance
      metadata remain available as filters that can be applied alongside, or after, the
      similarity search to narrow candidates.</para>

    <para>Examples of vector databases that support this style of retrieval include, without
      limitation, LanceDB, Milvus, Weaviate, Qdrant, and pgvector, a vector extension for
      PostgreSQL. Naming these products is illustrative only and does not constitute an
      endorsement or a requirement to use any of them.</para>

    <para>Continuing the example from <link linkend="xmlDatabaseApproach">XML-Aware Database and XPath Retrieval</link>, the same
      two entries could instead be indexed as vectors, each referencing the
      <code>&lt;unit></code> and originating <code>&lt;file></code> it was derived from
      (embedding values abbreviated for illustration):</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">tm-0002  original=manual/chapter3.html  "Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year."  [0.114, -0.028, 0.301, ...]
tm-1001  original=app/ui-strings.json   "Download your certificate before the end of the fiscal year."  [0.109, -0.031, 0.298, ...]</programlisting>

    <para>Unlike an XPath query, a similarity search is not limited to exact text. A query using
      a paraphrase of the same request, which shares no exact wording with either stored
      segment:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">"Please download your tax certificate before the fiscal year ends."</programlisting>

    <para>is converted to an embedding and compared against the indexed vectors, returning both
      <code>tm-0002</code> and <code>tm-1001</code> ranked by similarity score (for example,
      0.93 for each), even though an XPath query for this exact string, as in <link linkend="xmlDatabaseApproach">XML-Aware Database and        XPath Retrieval</link>, would return no results at all. As in that example, restricting
      the search to vectors whose <code>original</code> metadata equals
      <code>manual/chapter3.html</code> narrows the result to <code>tm-0002</code> alone.</para>

    <para>Semantic similarity alone has a known blind spot: embeddings can rank a candidate that
      changes the meaning nearly as highly as one that only changes the wording. Combining
      semantic similarity with a string-similarity ("fuzzy") metric into a single blended score,
      rather than using either alone, addresses this: a fuzzy string comparison of the same
      candidates penalizes that difference, while still tolerating the minor spelling or
      punctuation variation that an exact-text query would reject outright. Blending the two, for
      example by averaging a semantic similarity score with a string-similarity score such as
      longest-common-subsequence, gives a single ranking that neither method reliably produces on
      its own.</para>

    <para>A vector database's own distance metric only measures how similar a candidate is to
      the query; it has no notion of what that candidate cost to produce. Where a harvested
      entry's <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> chain, described in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for        Translation Memory Entries</link>, includes a <code>&lt;pvn:usage></code> element,
      implementers SHOULD map its text value alongside its <code>usageUnit</code> attribute as
      additional metadata fields on the indexed vector. Because <code>&lt;pvn:usage></code>
      records the computational cost of producing a change, for example the number of tokens a
      machine translation agent consumed to generate a target, a similarity search can then
      weight or filter candidates by that cost in addition to similarity score, for instance
      preferring a historical match that required fewer tokens to produce over an equally
      similar one that required more. This is particularly relevant when a TM lookup feeds a
      retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) translation workflow, where token cost and latency are
      part of what is being optimized.</para>
  </section>

  <para>Beyond translation-pair lookup, a concordance-style search, returning every stored entry
    whose <code>&lt;source></code> or <code>&lt;target></code> contains a given text
    fragment across every language present in the store, is a common complementary query mode.
    Either approach in this section can support it: an XPath <code>contains()</code> predicate
    for an XML-aware database, or a plain substring or full-text index alongside the vector index
    for a vector database. It is particularly useful for terminology review and quality checks
    that are not aimed at finding a reusable translation.</para>
</section>
  <section id="safetySecurity">
  <title>Safety, Security, and Data Protection Considerations</title>

  <para>Translation memory content frequently originates from source documents that were never
    intended for public redistribution, and may contain personal data or confidential business
    information carried over from the original text. Storing that content as plain XLIFF,
    rather than as an opaque TM database, does not change its sensitivity; implementers SHOULD
    apply the same access controls, storage protections, and redistribution policies to
    XLIFF-based TM files and packages as they would to any other document containing the same
    source content.</para>

  <para>The Provenance module attributes described in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for Translation Memory Entries</link>,
    in particular <code>person</code>, can themselves constitute personal data about the
    translators and reviewers who worked on the content. Implementers SHOULD consider
    applicable data protection requirements (such as consent and retention limits) before
    populating, storing, or exchanging <code>person</code> values in translation memory data,
    and MAY omit <code>person</code> in favor of <code>agent</code>, <code>organization</code>,
    or <code>tool</code> where individual identification is not required.</para>

  <para>Translation memory exchange packages, as described in <link linkend="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</link>, are
    ordinary ZIP archives. Implementations that unpack them SHOULD apply the same precautions
    recommended for processing any untrusted ZIP archive, including validating that archive
    entries do not escape the intended extraction directory (path traversal) and guarding
    against archives crafted to consume excessive disk space or memory when decompressed.</para>
</section>
  <section id="conformance">
  <title>Conformance</title>

  <section id="tmStoreConformance">
    <title>Translation Memory Store</title>

    <para>An XLIFF document <emphasis role="bold">conforms</emphasis> to this document as a
      <emphasis>Translation Memory Store</emphasis> if:</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
      <listitem>
        <para>It is a conformant [XLIFF-2.3-part2] (or later) document.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Every stored translation memory entry is represented as an XLIFF
          <code>&lt;unit></code> containing one <code>&lt;segment></code> per entry, with
          <code>&lt;source></code> and, where a translation is available,
          <code>&lt;target></code> content, and no lossy conversion of inline content has
          been applied to represent that entry.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Where provenance information is recorded for an entry, it is expressed using the
          XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module rather than free-text notes or properties.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="tmPackageConformance">
    <title>Translation Memory Exchange Package</title>

    <para>A ZIP archive <emphasis role="bold">conforms</emphasis> to this document as a
      <emphasis>Translation Memory Exchange Package</emphasis> if:</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
      <listitem>
        <para>It contains an <code>xliff-manifest.xml</code> file at its root, as described in <link linkend="manifestFile">Manifest File</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Every XLIFF file listed in the manifest is present in the archive and conforms to
          this document as a Translation Memory Store.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Every XLIFF file listed in the manifest declares a single <code>srcLang</code>,
          matching the <code>srcLang</code> of the aligned set that contains it, and a single
          <code>trgLang</code>, matching the <code>trgLang</code> recorded for that file in the
          manifest.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>For every aligned set in the manifest with more than one member, corresponding
          translation units across the member files use the same <code>&lt;unit></code>
          <code>id</code> value (and, where segmented, the same <code>&lt;segment></code>
          <code>id</code> value), as described in <link linkend="packageStructure">Package Structure</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Where a <code>&lt;file></code> entry in the manifest carries a
          <code>hash</code> attribute, the content of the file it references matches that
          hash.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>

  
  <appendix id="annexA" role="normative">
  <title>License, Document Status and Notices</title>

  <section id="documentStatus">
    <title>Document Status</title>

    <para>This document was last revised or approved by the OASIS XLIFF TC on the above date.
      The level of approval is also listed above. Check the "Latest version" location noted
      above for possible later revisions of this document. Any other numbered Versions and
      other technical work produced by the Technical Committee (TC) are listed at <ulink url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf#technical">https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf#technical</ulink>.</para>

    <para>TC members should send comments on this document to the TC's email list. Others
      should send comments to the TC's public comment list, after subscribing to it by
      following the comment instructions at the TC's comments list web page at <ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=xliff">https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=xliff</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="licenseAndNotices">
    <title>License and Notices</title>

    <para>Copyright © OASIS Open 2026. All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings assigned to them in the
      OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the "OASIS IPR Policy"). The full Policy, which
      governs the licensure of this document, may be found at the OASIS website: [<ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/">https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/</ulink>]</para>

    <para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to others, and
      derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it or assist in its implementation
      may be prepared, copied, published, and distributed, in whole or in part, without
      restriction of any kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this section are
      included on all such copies and derivative works. However, this document itself may not
      be modified in any way, including by removing the copyright notice or references to
      OASIS, except as needed for the purpose of developing any document or deliverable
      produced by an OASIS Technical Committee (in which case the rules applicable to
      copyrights, as set forth in the OASIS IPR Policy, must be followed) or as required to
      translate it into languages other than English.</para>

    <para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be revoked by OASIS
      or its successors or assigns, as provided in the OASIS IPR Policy.</para>

    <para>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an "AS IS" basis
      and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY
      WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP RIGHTS OR
      ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. OASIS AND
      ITS MEMBERS WILL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
      ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THIS DOCUMENT OR ANY PART THEREOF.</para>

    <para>The name "OASIS" is a trademark of OASIS, the owner and developer of this document,
      and should be used only to refer to the organization and its official outputs. OASIS
      welcomes reference to, and implementation and use of, its documents, while reserving the
      right to enforce its marks against misleading uses. Please see <ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/">https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/</ulink> for guidance.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
  <appendix id="annexB">
  <title>References</title>

  <para>This section contains the normative and informative references that are used in this document.</para>

  <para>Informative references are either specific or non-specific. For specific references,
    only the cited version applies. For non-specific references, the latest version of the
    reference document (including any amendments) applies. While any hyperlinks included in
    this section were valid at the time of publication, OASIS cannot guarantee their long term
    validity.</para>

  <section id="normativeReferences">
    <title>Normative References</title>

    <bibliography>
      <title/>
      <bibliomixed id="xliff23part2"><abbrev>XLIFF-2.3-part2</abbrev> XLIFF Version 2.3 Part 2:
        Extended. Edited by Rodolfo M. Raya and Lucía Morado Vázquez. 8 July 2026. OASIS
        Committee Specification Draft 01. <citetitle><ulink url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.3/xliff-v2.3-part2-extended.html">https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.3/xliff-v2.3-part2-extended.html</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed id="rfc2119"><abbrev>RFC2119</abbrev> S. Bradner. <title>Key words for use
          in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>. March 1997. <citetitle><ulink url="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119">https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed id="zipAppnote"><abbrev>ZIP APPNOTE</abbrev> PKWARE, Inc. <title>.ZIP File
          Format Specification</title>. <citetitle><ulink url="https://pkware.cachefly.net/webdocs/casestudies/APPNOTE.TXT">https://pkware.cachefly.net/webdocs/casestudies/APPNOTE.TXT</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </section>

  <section id="informativeReferences">
    <title>Informative References</title>

    <para>The following referenced documents are not required for the application of this
      document but may assist the reader with regard to a particular subject area.</para>

    <bibliography>
      <title/>
      <bibliomixed id="tmx14b"><abbrev>TMX 1.4b</abbrev> Translation Memory eXchange (TMX)
        Version 1.4b. Edited by Yves Savourel. OSCAR Recommendation, 26 April 2005.
        <citetitle><ulink url="https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed id="xliff23provenance"><abbrev>XLIFF-2.3-provenance</abbrev> XLIFF Version
        2.3 Provenance Module (Work in Progress). OASIS XLIFF Technical Committee. Not yet
        published; referenced here for context while under development in the same working
        repository as this document.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </section>
</appendix>

  
  <appendix id="acknowledgements" role="informative">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>

  <section id="ackLeadership">
    <title>Leadership</title>

    <para>The following individuals have had significant leadership positions during the
      development of this document, not just this version of the document, and they are
      gratefully acknowledged:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Chairs</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Dr. Lucía Morado Vázquez, University of Geneva</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Yoshito Umaoka, Individual</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Secretaries</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Rodolfo M. Raya, Maxprograms</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Editors</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Rodolfo M. Raya, Maxprograms</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="ackSpecialThanks">
    <title>Special Thanks</title>

    <para>The following individuals have made substantial contributions to this document, not
      just this version of the document, and their contributions are gratefully
      acknowledged:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Mihai Niță, Google LLC</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mathijs Sonnemans, Individual</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="ackParticipants">
    <title>Participants</title>

    <para>The following individuals were members of this committee during the creation of this
      document, not just this version of the document, and their contributions are gratefully
      acknowledged:</para>

    <para><emphasis>&lt; Placeholder: full list of individuals who were members of the OASIS
      XLIFF TC during the creation of this document. ></emphasis></para>
  </section>
</appendix>
  <appendix id="changeTracking" role="informative">
  <title>Changes From Previous Version</title>

  <para>None. This is the first published draft of this document.</para>

  <section id="revisionHistory">
    <title>Revision History</title>

    <para>None.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>

</article>