<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en-US" status="Committee Note Draft 01">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>XLIFF Translation Memory Version 1.0</title>

    <productname class="trade">xliff-tm</productname>

    <productnumber>cnd01</productnumber>

    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-this-authoritative">[ link to authoritative version of the published document ]</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous-authoritative">[ link to authoritative version of the published document ]</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-latest-authoritative">[ link to authoritative version of the published document ]</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="committee"><ulink url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf">OASIS
        XLIFF TC</ulink></releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <othercredit role="chair">
        <honorific>Dr</honorific>
        <firstname>Lucía</firstname>
        <surname>Morado Vázquez</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink url="https://www.unige.ch/en/">University of Geneva</ulink></orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>lucia.morado@unige.ch</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>lucia.morado@unige.ch</email>
      </othercredit>
      <othercredit role="chair">
        <firstname>Yoshito</firstname>
        <surname>Umaoka</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Individual</orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>y.umaoka@gmail.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>y.umaoka@gmail.com</email>
      </othercredit>
      <othercredit role="secretary">
        <firstname>Rodolfo M.</firstname>
        <surname>Raya</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink url="https://maxprograms.com">Maxprograms</ulink></orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email>
      </othercredit>
      <editor>
        <firstname>Rodolfo M.</firstname>
        <surname>Raya</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink url="https://maxprograms.com">Maxprograms</ulink></orgname>
          <address format="linespecific"><email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
        <email>rmraya@maxprograms.com</email>
      </editor>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>8 July 2025</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2025</year>
      <holder>OASIS Open, Inc. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice role="related">
      <title>Related Work</title>

      <para>This document replaces or supersedes:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>[ The full reference to the related document in IEEE reference format ]</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This document is related to:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="strong">[XLIFF-2.2-part2]</emphasis> XLIFF Version 2.2 Part 2:
            Extended. Edited by Rodolfo M. Raya and Lucía Morado Vázquez 13 March 2025. OASIS
            Committee Specification. <ulink url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.2/xliff-v2.2-part2-extended.html">https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.2/xliff-v2.2-part2-extended.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="strong">[TMX 1.4b]</emphasis> Translation Memory eXchange (TMX)
            Version 1.4b. Edited by Yves Savourel. OSCAR Recommendation, 26 April 2005. <ulink url="https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This Committee Note describes an XLIFF-native approach for the representation and
        exchange of translation memory data, using plain XLIFF <code>&lt;file></code>,
        <code>&lt;unit></code>, and <code>&lt;segment></code> elements as the translation
        memory store itself, in place of the Translation Memory eXchange (TMX) format. The
        approach preserves the structure and semantics of XLIFF content, including bilingual
        text, inline elements, segmentation, and associated metadata, without the information
        loss that results from converting content to and from TMX's inline tag model. It also
        preserves the document order and structural relationship between translation units,
        file, unit, and segment, that TMX's flat, unordered list of translation units does not
        represent, and it allows richer metadata, such as provenance information, to be attached
        directly using existing XLIFF modules.</para>

      <para>This Committee Note also addresses the exchange of translation memory data for
        multilingual use. Because XLIFF documents are fundamentally bilingual, the Note
        recommends a packaging approach in which multiple related bilingual XLIFF files are
        distributed together in a single ZIP package with a manifest that identifies the
        relationships among them.</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice role="citation">
      <title>Citation format</title>
      <para>When referencing this document, the following citation format should be used:</para>
      <para>[ The full reference for this document in IEEE reference format ]</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice role="notices">
      <title>License, Document Status, and Notices</title>

      <para>Copyright © OASIS Open 2025. All Rights Reserved. For license and copyright
        information, and complete status, please see Annex A which contains the License,
        Document Status and Notices.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="scope">
  <title>Scope</title>

  <para>This Committee Note describes an XLIFF-native approach for storing and exchanging
    translation memory (TM) data, using plain XLIFF 2.x documents in place of the Translation
    Memory eXchange (TMX) format.</para>

  <para>Rather than defining a new container or converting bilingual content into a separate
    TM-specific format, this document recommends that XLIFF <code>&lt;file></code>,
    <code>&lt;unit></code>, and <code>&lt;segment></code> elements be used directly to hold
    translation units for later reuse. This preserves the full XLIFF inline element model,
    avoiding the loss of information that results from converting XLIFF inline markup to and
    from the TMX inline tag model, and preserves the structural order of content, which TMX's
    flat, unordered list of <code>&lt;tu></code> elements does not represent.</para>

  <para>This document also describes how the XLIFF Provenance module, under development for
    XLIFF 2.3, can be used to record and later query information about the origin of stored
    translation units, such as the agent, tool, or process that produced or modified them.</para>

  <para>Because a single XLIFF document is inherently bilingual, this document further describes
    a packaging convention for exchanging translation memory data across more than two
    languages, based on a set of related bilingual XLIFF files distributed together with a
    manifest.</para>
</section>
  <section id="definitionsAndAcronyms">
  <title>Definitions and Acronyms</title>

  <section id="definitions">
    <title>Definitions</title>

    <section id="termsDefinedElsewhere">
      <title>Terms Defined Elsewhere</title>

      <para>This document uses the following terms defined elsewhere:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Unit [XLIFF-2.2-part2]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>"A <code>&lt;unit></code> MAY contain both source and target content,
              allowing bilingual data to be stored."</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Segment [XLIFF-2.2-part2]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <code>&lt;segment></code> element, used to represent the smallest unit
              of translatable content addressed for translation, review, or other
              processing.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Provenance information [Provenance module, XLIFF 2.3, informative]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Information about the nature and origin of the localization data or
              process.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section id="termsDefinedInThisDocument">
      <title>Terms Defined in this Document</title>

      <para>This document defines the following terms:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation memory (TM)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A collection of previously translated source and target content, organized
              for retrieval and reuse when equal or similar source content is encountered
              again.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation memory entry</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A single stored source/target pair available for reuse, represented in this
              document as an XLIFF <code>&lt;unit></code> (or, where segmented,
              <code>&lt;segment></code>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation memory exchange package</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A ZIP archive containing one or more bilingual XLIFF files together with a
              manifest, used to exchange translation memory data across more than two
              languages, as described in <link linkend="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="abbreviationsAndAcronyms">
    <title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>

    <para>This document uses the following abbreviations and acronyms:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>TC: Technical Committee</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TM: Translation Memory</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TMX: Translation Memory eXchange</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TU: Translation Unit</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>TUV: Translation Unit Variant (TMX)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>XML: Extensible Markup Language</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>ZIP: A common archive file format</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="documentConventions">
  <title>Document Conventions</title>

  <section id="keyWords">
    <title>Key Words</title>

    <para>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
      NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in <link linkend="rfc2119">[RFC2119]</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="typographicalConventions">
    <title>Typographical Conventions</title>

    <para>XML element names are shown enclosed in angle brackets, for example
      <code>&lt;unit></code>. XML attribute names are shown in fixed-width type without
      brackets, for example <code>id</code>. XML namespace prefixes used in examples
      (<code>xlf:</code>, <code>mtc:</code>, <code>pvn:</code>) follow the conventions
      established in [XLIFF-2.2-part2] and the XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module. Example XML is shown
      in fenced code blocks and is illustrative; it is not necessarily complete or
      schema-valid.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>Translation memory (TM) is a core technology of the localization industry. A TM stores
    previously translated content so that it can be retrieved and reused when equal or similar
    source content is encountered again, improving consistency and reducing translation effort
    and cost.</para>

  <para>Since 2005, the de facto standard for exchanging TM data between tools has been the
    Translation Memory eXchange (TMX) format [TMX 1.4b]. TMX was designed as a vendor-neutral
    interchange format, independent of any single authoring or extraction format. XLIFF, by
    contrast, is designed to carry bilingual (and, through packaging, multilingual) content
    through the localization process itself, from extraction through translation, review, and
    reintegration into the original format.</para>

  <para>As XLIFF adoption has grown, and as the XLIFF inline content model, segmentation model,
    and metadata modules have become richer, the gap between what an XLIFF document can
    represent and what TMX can represent has widened. Producing a TMX export of translated
    content, or importing TMX leverage into an XLIFF-based workflow, requires a conversion step.
    That conversion step is where information is put at risk.</para>

  <section id="tmxLimitations">
    <title>Limitations of TMX-Based Exchange</title>

    <para>TMX and XLIFF do not share an inline content model. TMX represents inline markup with
      a small, generic set of placeholder elements (<code>&lt;bpt></code>,
      <code>&lt;ept></code>, <code>&lt;it></code>, <code>&lt;ph></code>,
      <code>&lt;hi></code>) that carry no structural relationship to the original markup
      beyond matched pairing and free-form type/i attributes. XLIFF represents inline content
      with a richer, self-describing model (<code>&lt;pc></code>, <code>&lt;sc></code>,
      <code>&lt;ec></code>, <code>&lt;ph></code>, <code>&lt;mrk></code>,
      <code>&lt;sm></code>/<code>&lt;em></code>, backed by
      <code>&lt;originalData></code>). Converting XLIFF inline content into TMX inline
      content, and back again, is a lossy, implementation-specific mapping. There is no
      guarantee that a round trip through TMX preserves the original XLIFF markup, and in
      practice it frequently does not.</para>

    <para>TMX is defined by a Document Type Definition (DTD), not an XML Schema, and a TMX
      document is a self-contained top-level document with its own DOCTYPE. A TMX
      <code>&lt;tu></code> cannot be embedded inside an XLIFF document, and an XLIFF
      <code>&lt;unit></code> cannot be embedded inside a TMX document. The two formats can
      only be related to each other through external conversion, never through direct inclusion.
      This also means TMX content cannot participate in XLIFF's own extension and modularization
      mechanisms, such as the Translation Candidates module (<code>mtc:matches</code>, see
      [XLIFF-2.2-part2]), which is designed to hold XLIFF-native
      <code>&lt;source></code>/<code>&lt;target></code> pairs as leveraging matches inside
      a unit.</para>

    <para>Finally, a TMX file is a flat, unordered collection of <code>&lt;tu></code>
      elements. TMX defines no relationship between one translation unit and the next; any
      notion of document order, or of which segments originally appeared near each other, is
      lost once content is exported to TMX (short of ad hoc use of <code>&lt;prop></code> or
      <code>&lt;note></code> elements to reconstruct it). XLIFF does not have this
      limitation: an XLIFF document is structured as <code>&lt;file></code> containing one or
      more <code>&lt;unit></code> elements, each containing one or more
      <code>&lt;segment></code> elements, and that hierarchy is preserved in document order.
      Two segments that are adjacent in an XLIFF file are known to be adjacent in the source
      content, which is valuable context for TM leveraging, concordance search, and quality
      review that a flat TMX export cannot provide.</para>

    <para>For these reasons, this document recommends that plain XLIFF documents be used
      directly as the storage and interchange format for translation memory data, rather than
      converting content to and from TMX.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="changesFromPreviousVersion">
    <title>Changes From the Previous Version</title>

    <para>The list of changes from the previous version and any revision history can be found in
      Appendix 2.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="tmFormat">
  <title>XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</title>

  <para>This section describes the recommended approach for storing translation memory data as
    plain XLIFF documents, using XLIFF Core elements as they are already defined, without
    introducing a new TM-specific vocabulary.</para>

  <section id="designPrinciples">
    <title>Design Principles</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">No conversion.</emphasis> A TM entry is an XLIFF
          <code>&lt;unit></code> containing one or more <code>&lt;segment></code>
          elements with <code>&lt;source></code> and <code>&lt;target></code> content,
          exactly as produced by any XLIFF-conformant extraction, translation, or review tool.
          Storing that content as translation memory requires no transformation of inline
          markup, and retrieving it for reuse in another XLIFF document requires no
          transformation back.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Full inline fidelity.</emphasis> Because TM entries remain
          XLIFF <code>&lt;unit></code> elements, they retain the full XLIFF inline element
          model (<code>&lt;pc></code>, <code>&lt;sc></code>/<code>&lt;ec></code>,
          <code>&lt;ph></code>, <code>&lt;mrk></code>,
          <code>&lt;sm></code>/<code>&lt;em></code>) together with any associated
          <code>&lt;originalData></code>, instead of being reduced to the smaller TMX inline
          tag set.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Preserved order.</emphasis> Units and segments remain in
          the document order in which they were extracted, inside their originating
          <code>&lt;file></code> (and, where used, <code>&lt;group></code>). See <link linkend="structuralOrder">Structural Order and Segment            Context</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Extensibility through existing modules.</emphasis> Any
          XLIFF module that can annotate a <code>&lt;file></code>, <code>&lt;unit></code>,
          or <code>&lt;segment></code> in a normal XLIFF document, such as metadata, notes,
          size and length restriction, or the Provenance module described in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for            Translation Memory Entries</link>, applies equally when that document is used as a
          TM store. No parallel metadata model is required.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="structuralOrder">
    <title>Structural Order and Segment Context</title>

    <para>TMX represents a translation memory as a flat, unordered collection of
      <code>&lt;tu></code> elements. TMX defines no relationship between one translation
      unit and any other; the position of a <code>&lt;tu></code> in a TMX file carries no
      meaning.</para>

    <para>An XLIFF document used as a TM store retains the <code>&lt;file></code> >
      <code>&lt;unit></code> > <code>&lt;segment></code> hierarchy defined by XLIFF
      Core. This hierarchy carries information that a flat TU list cannot:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Document order</emphasis> is preserved. Segments that were
          adjacent in the original content remain adjacent, which supports context-aware
          leveraging (for example, preferring a match whose neighboring segments also match)
          and concordance search that shows a hit in its original surrounding context.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Provenance of the source document</emphasis> is preserved.
          The enclosing <code>&lt;file></code> retains attributes such as
          <code>original</code>, and can carry <code>&lt;file></code>-level metadata, so
          that every stored <code>&lt;unit></code> remains traceable to the document it came
          from.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Grouping</emphasis> is preserved. Where the source content
          used <code>&lt;group></code> to represent structural divisions (chapters, UI
          screens, table rows, and so on), those divisions remain available to a TM consumer,
          instead of being discarded at export time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A translation memory consumer that only needs unordered TU-style lookup can still
      treat every <code>&lt;segment></code> in every <code>&lt;unit></code> of every
      <code>&lt;file></code> as an independent entry, exactly as it would treat entries in a
      TMX file. The XLIFF-based representation is a strict superset of that capability: it does
      not require order and context to be used, but it does not discard them either.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="provenanceMetadata">
    <title>Provenance Metadata for Translation Memory Entries</title>

    <para>Reuse decisions in a translation memory workflow are often qualified by information
      about the origin of a given entry: who or what produced or last modified it, when, using
      what tool, and why. TMX addresses this only partially, through the
      <code>creationid</code>, <code>creationdate</code>, <code>changeid</code>,
      <code>changedate</code>, and <code>&lt;prop></code>/<code>&lt;note></code>
      mechanisms defined for <code>&lt;tu></code> and <code>&lt;tuv></code>.</para>

    <para>The XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module (<code>pvn:</code>, under development by the OASIS
      XLIFF TC, see the <code>xliff-23</code> provenance module in this repository) is designed
      to record equivalent, and richer, information directly on XLIFF Core elements, using the
      <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code> and <code>&lt;pvn:change></code> elements and
      attributes such as <code>agent</code>, <code>person</code>, <code>organization</code>,
      <code>tool</code>, <code>timestamp</code>, <code>appliesTo</code>, and
      <code>intent</code>. Because a TM entry stored as described in this document is an
      ordinary XLIFF <code>&lt;unit></code>, it can carry <code>&lt;pvn:provenance></code>
      metadata exactly as any other XLIFF unit can.</para>

    <para>This gives a translation memory consumer the ability to query stored entries by their
      provenance, for example to prefer entries produced by a specific translator or reviewed
      by a specific organization, to exclude machine-translated entries that were never
      reviewed by a person, or to filter by the date a translation was performed. Since
      provenance metadata is expressed using XLIFF elements and attributes rather than
      free-text <code>&lt;prop></code> values, as TMX requires, it can be validated and
      queried using standard XML tooling.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tmFormatExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A single translated document only ever has one <code>&lt;file></code>, so nothing
      about it shows translation memory <emphasis>reuse</emphasis>. The following example
      instead shows a TM store: an XLIFF document aggregating entries extracted from two
      unrelated projects, translated five months apart. The second project reuses a sentence
      already translated for the first, which is exactly the situation a translation memory
      exists to detect and exploit. Because both projects remain inside a single XLIFF
      document, each entry stays traceable to the <code>&lt;file></code> (and therefore the
      project) it came from, in the order it was added to the store, which a flat TMX
      <code>&lt;tu></code> list cannot represent.</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific"></programlisting>

    <para>Because <code>tm-1001</code> and <code>tm-0002</code> share the same
      <code>&lt;source></code> text, a TM consumer can find the reuse with a plain text
      comparison across the store, exactly as it would across a flat TMX file, then attribute
      that reuse using the Provenance module's <code>intent</code> attribute instead of a
      free-text TMX <code>&lt;prop></code>. And because both entries remain inside
      <code>&lt;file></code> elements that retain their own <code>original</code> attribute,
      the store also records which project each translation came from and in what order it was
      added, something a TMX export of the same two projects would have discarded.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="exchange">
  <title>Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</title>

  <para>An XLIFF document is bilingual: it declares a single <code>srcLang</code> and a single
    <code>trgLang</code>. A translation memory, however, is often required to hold or exchange
    content across more than two languages. TMX addresses this within a single file, because a
    <code>&lt;tu></code> can hold any number of <code>&lt;tuv></code> elements, one per
    language.</para>

  <para>This document recommends addressing the same requirement not by making an individual
    XLIFF document multilingual, which would be a departure from the XLIFF Core data model, but
    by packaging multiple bilingual XLIFF files together, one per source/target language pair,
    along with a manifest that identifies the relationship among them. This keeps every
    individual file fully conformant with, and processable by, any existing XLIFF 2.x tool,
    while still allowing a translation memory covering many languages to be exchanged as a
    single unit.</para>

  <section id="packageStructure">
    <title>Package Structure</title>

    <para>A translation memory exchange package is a ZIP archive (as defined in [ZIP APPNOTE])
      with the following content:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more bilingual XLIFF files, each conforming to [XLIFF-2.2-part2] or later,
          sharing a common <code>srcLang</code> and each declaring its own
          <code>trgLang</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A single manifest file, described in <link linkend="manifestFile">Manifest File</link>, that lists the XLIFF files in the
          package and the language pair each one represents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Corresponding translation units across the language-pair files in a package SHOULD
      use the same <code>&lt;unit></code> <code>id</code> value (and, where segmented, the
      same <code>&lt;segment></code> <code>id</code> value) so that a consumer can align
      entries for the same source content across target languages. This mirrors, at the
      package level, the alignment that a multilingual <code>&lt;tu></code> provides in a
      single TMX file.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="manifestFile">
    <title>Manifest File</title>

    <para>The manifest is an XML file, named <code>manifest.xml</code>, placed at the root of
      the package. It lists each XLIFF file contained in the package together with its source
      and target language.</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific"></programlisting>

    <para><emphasis>The manifest namespace, element and attribute names, and XML Schema shown
      above are provisional and subject to review by the OASIS XLIFF TC before this Note
      advances beyond Committee Note Draft.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="exchangeExample">
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>A translation memory covering English source content with Spanish, French, and
      German target content would be packaged as:</para>

    <programlisting format="linespecific">tm-package.zip
├── manifest.xml
├── en-es.xlf
├── en-fr.xlf
└── en-de.xlf</programlisting>

    <para>Each of <code>en-es.xlf</code>, <code>en-fr.xlf</code>, and <code>en-de.xlf</code> is
      an ordinary bilingual XLIFF document as described in <link linkend="tmFormat">XLIFF as a Translation Memory Format</link>, and each can be
      consumed independently by a tool that only needs one language pair, or together by a tool
      that reads <code>manifest.xml</code> to reconstruct the full multilingual set.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  <section id="safetySecurity">
  <title>Safety, Security, and Data Protection Considerations</title>

  <para>Translation memory content frequently originates from source documents that were never
    intended for public redistribution, and may contain personal data or confidential business
    information carried over from the original text. Storing that content as plain XLIFF,
    rather than as an opaque TM database, does not change its sensitivity; implementers SHOULD
    apply the same access controls, storage protections, and redistribution policies to
    XLIFF-based TM files and packages as they would to any other document containing the same
    source content.</para>

  <para>The Provenance module attributes described in <link linkend="provenanceMetadata">Provenance Metadata for Translation Memory Entries</link>,
    in particular <code>person</code>, can themselves constitute personal data about the
    translators and reviewers who worked on the content. Implementers SHOULD consider
    applicable data protection requirements (such as consent and retention limits) before
    populating, storing, or exchanging <code>person</code> values in translation memory data,
    and MAY omit <code>person</code> in favor of <code>agent</code>, <code>organization</code>,
    or <code>tool</code> where individual identification is not required.</para>

  <para>Translation memory exchange packages, as described in <link linkend="exchange">Exchange of Multilingual Translation Memory Data</link>, are
    ordinary ZIP archives. Implementations that unpack them SHOULD apply the same precautions
    recommended for processing any untrusted ZIP archive, including validating that archive
    entries do not escape the intended extraction directory (path traversal) and guarding
    against archives crafted to consume excessive disk space or memory when decompressed.</para>
</section>
  <section id="conformance">
  <title>Conformance</title>

  <section id="tmStoreConformance">
    <title>Translation Memory Store</title>

    <para>An XLIFF document <emphasis role="bold">conforms</emphasis> to this document as a
      <emphasis>Translation Memory Store</emphasis> if:</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
      <listitem>
        <para>It is a conformant [XLIFF-2.2-part2] (or later) document.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Every stored translation memory entry is represented as an XLIFF
          <code>&lt;unit></code> containing one <code>&lt;segment></code> per entry, with
          <code>&lt;source></code> and, where a translation is available,
          <code>&lt;target></code> content, and no lossy conversion of inline content has
          been applied to represent that entry.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Where provenance information is recorded for an entry, it is expressed using the
          XLIFF 2.3 Provenance module rather than free-text notes or properties.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="tmPackageConformance">
    <title>Translation Memory Exchange Package</title>

    <para>A ZIP archive <emphasis role="bold">conforms</emphasis> to this document as a
      <emphasis>Translation Memory Exchange Package</emphasis> if:</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
      <listitem>
        <para>It contains a <code>manifest.xml</code> file at its root, as described in <link linkend="manifestFile">Manifest File</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Every XLIFF file listed in the manifest is present in the archive and conforms to
          this document as a Translation Memory Store.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Every XLIFF file listed in the manifest declares a single <code>srcLang</code>
          and a single <code>trgLang</code>, matching the language pair recorded for that file
          in the manifest.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>

  
  <appendix id="annexA" role="normative">
  <title>License, Document Status and Notices</title>

  <section id="documentStatus">
    <title>Document Status</title>

    <para>This document was last revised or approved by the OASIS XLIFF TC on the above date.
      The level of approval is also listed above. Check the "Latest version" location noted
      above for possible later revisions of this document. Any other numbered Versions and
      other technical work produced by the Technical Committee (TC) are listed at <ulink url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf#technical">https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf#technical</ulink>.</para>

    <para>TC members should send comments on this document to the TC's email list. Others
      should send comments to the TC's public comment list, after subscribing to it by
      following the comment instructions at the TC's comments list web page at <ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=xliff">https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=xliff</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="licenseAndNotices">
    <title>License and Notices</title>

    <para>Copyright © OASIS Open 2026. All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings assigned to them in the
      OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the "OASIS IPR Policy"). The full Policy, which
      governs the licensure of this document, may be found at the OASIS website: [<ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/">https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/</ulink>]</para>

    <para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to others, and
      derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it or assist in its implementation
      may be prepared, copied, published, and distributed, in whole or in part, without
      restriction of any kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this section are
      included on all such copies and derivative works. However, this document itself may not
      be modified in any way, including by removing the copyright notice or references to
      OASIS, except as needed for the purpose of developing any document or deliverable
      produced by an OASIS Technical Committee (in which case the rules applicable to
      copyrights, as set forth in the OASIS IPR Policy, must be followed) or as required to
      translate it into languages other than English.</para>

    <para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be revoked by OASIS
      or its successors or assigns, as provided in the OASIS IPR Policy.</para>

    <para>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an "AS IS" basis
      and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY
      WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP RIGHTS OR
      ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. OASIS AND
      ITS MEMBERS WILL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
      ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THIS DOCUMENT OR ANY PART THEREOF.</para>

    <para>The name "OASIS" is a trademark of OASIS, the owner and developer of this document,
      and should be used only to refer to the organization and its official outputs. OASIS
      welcomes reference to, and implementation and use of, its documents, while reserving the
      right to enforce its marks against misleading uses. Please see <ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/">https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/</ulink> for guidance.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
  <appendix id="annexB">
  <title>References</title>

  <para>This section contains the normative and informative references that are used in this document.</para>

  <para>Informative references are either specific or non-specific. For specific references,
    only the cited version applies. For non-specific references, the latest version of the
    reference document (including any amendments) applies. While any hyperlinks included in
    this section were valid at the time of publication, OASIS cannot guarantee their long term
    validity.</para>

  <section id="normativeReferences">
    <title>Normative References</title>

    <bibliography>
      <title/>
      <bibliomixed id="xliff22part2"><abbrev>XLIFF-2.2-part2</abbrev> XLIFF Version 2.2 Part 2:
        Extended. Edited by Rodolfo M. Raya and Lucía Morado Vázquez. 13 March 2025. OASIS
        Committee Specification. <citetitle><ulink url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.2/xliff-v2.2-part2-extended.html">https://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/xliff-core/v2.2/xliff-v2.2-part2-extended.html</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed id="rfc2119"><abbrev>RFC2119</abbrev> S. Bradner. <title>Key words for use
          in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>. March 1997. <citetitle><ulink url="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119">https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed id="zipAppnote"><abbrev>ZIP APPNOTE</abbrev> PKWARE, Inc. <title>.ZIP File
          Format Specification</title>. <citetitle><ulink url="https://pkware.cachefly.net/webdocs/casestudies/APPNOTE.TXT">https://pkware.cachefly.net/webdocs/casestudies/APPNOTE.TXT</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </section>

  <section id="informativeReferences">
    <title>Informative References</title>

    <para>The following referenced documents are not required for the application of this
      document but may assist the reader with regard to a particular subject area.</para>

    <bibliography>
      <title/>
      <bibliomixed id="tmx14b"><abbrev>TMX 1.4b</abbrev> Translation Memory eXchange (TMX)
        Version 1.4b. Edited by Yves Savourel. OSCAR Recommendation, 26 April 2005.
        <citetitle><ulink url="https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20060528180452/http://www.lisa.org/standards/tmx/tmx.html</ulink></citetitle>.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed id="xliff23provenance"><abbrev>XLIFF-2.3-provenance</abbrev> XLIFF Version
        2.3 Provenance Module (Work in Progress). OASIS XLIFF Technical Committee. Not yet
        published; referenced here for context while under development in the same working
        repository as this document.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </section>
</appendix>

  
  <appendix id="acknowledgements" role="informative">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>

  <section id="ackLeadership">
    <title>Leadership</title>

    <para>The following individuals have had significant leadership positions during the
      development of this document, not just this version of the document, and they are
      gratefully acknowledged:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Chairs</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Dr. Lucía Morado Vázquez, University of Geneva</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Yoshito Umaoka, Individual</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Secretaries</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Rodolfo M. Raya, Maxprograms</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Editors</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Rodolfo M. Raya, Maxprograms</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="ackSpecialThanks">
    <title>Special Thanks</title>

    <para>The following individuals have made substantial contributions to this document, not
      just this version of the document, and their contributions are gratefully
      acknowledged:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Mihai Niță, Google LLC</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mathijs Sonnemans, Individual</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="ackParticipants">
    <title>Participants</title>

    <para>The following individuals were members of this committee during the creation of this
      document, not just this version of the document, and their contributions are gratefully
      acknowledged:</para>

    <para><emphasis>&lt; Placeholder: full list of individuals who were members of the OASIS
      XLIFF TC during the creation of this document. ></emphasis></para>
  </section>
</appendix>
  <appendix id="changeTracking" role="informative">
  <title>Changes From Previous Version</title>

  <para>None. This is the first published draft of this document.</para>

  <section id="revisionHistory">
    <title>Revision History</title>

    <para>None.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>

</article>