<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY % base SYSTEM "../docbook/dbgenent.mod">
%base;

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<appendix id="annexA">
    <title>License, Document Status and Notices</title>

    <para>(This annex forms an integral part of this Specification.)</para>

    <section id="documentStatus">
        <title>Document Status</title>

        <para>This document was last revised or approved by the XLIFF TC on the above date. The
            level of approval is also listed above. Check the "Latest stage" location noted above
            for possible later revisions of this document. Any other numbered Versions and other
            technical work produced by the Technical Committee (TC) are listed at <ulink
                url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf"
                >https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf</ulink>.</para>

        <para>TC members should send comments on this document to the TC's email list. Others
            should send comments to the TC's public comment list, after subscribing to it by
            following the instructions at <ulink
                url="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf"
                >https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=3d0f1f56-8477-4b53-9b14-018dc7d3eecf</ulink>.</para>

        <para>This document is provided under the <ulink
                url="https:https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/#RF-Rand">RF on RAND Terms</ulink> Mode of the <ulink
                url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/">OASIS IPR
                Policy</ulink>, the mode chosen when the Technical Committee was established. For
            information on whether any patents have been disclosed that may be essential to
            implementing this document, and any offers of patent licensing terms, please refer to
            the Intellectual Property Rights section of the TC's web page (<ulink
                url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/xliff/ipr.php"
                >https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/xliff/ipr.php</ulink>).</para>

        <para>NOTE: any machine-readable content (<ulink
                url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/tc-process-2017-05-26/#wpComponentsCompLang">Computer Language Definitions</ulink>) declared Normative for this
            Work Product is provided in separate plain text files. In the event of a discrepancy
            between any such plain text file and display content in the Work Product's prose
            narrative document(s), the content in the separate plain text file prevails.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="licenseAndNotices">
        <title>License and Notices</title>

        <para>Copyright © OASIS Open &pubyear;. All Rights Reserved.</para>

        <para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings assigned to them in
            the OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the "OASIS IPR Policy"). The full <ulink
                url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/">Policy</ulink> may be
            found at the OASIS website: [<ulink
                url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/"
                >https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/</ulink>].</para>

        <para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to others, and
            derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it or assist in its
            implementation may be prepared, copied, published, and distributed, in whole or in
            part, without restriction of any kind, provided that the above copyright notice and
            this section are included on all such copies and derivative works. However, this
            document itself may not be modified in any way, including by removing the copyright
            notice or references to OASIS, except as needed for the purpose of developing any
            document or deliverable produced by an OASIS Technical Committee (in which case the
            rules applicable to copyrights, as set forth in the OASIS IPR Policy, must be
            followed) or as required to translate it into languages other than English.</para>

        <para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be revoked by
            OASIS or its successors or assigns.</para>

        <para>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an "AS IS" basis
            and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO
            ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP
            RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
            PURPOSE. OASIS AND ITS MEMBERS WILL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL OR
            CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THIS DOCUMENT OR ANY PART THEREOF.</para>

        <para>As stated in the OASIS IPR Policy, the following three paragraphs in brackets apply
            to OASIS Standards Final Deliverable documents (Committee Specifications, OASIS
            Standards, or Approved Errata).</para>

        <para>[OASIS requests that any OASIS Party or any other party that believes it has patent
            claims that would necessarily be infringed by implementations of this OASIS Standards
            Final Deliverable, to notify OASIS TC Administrator and provide an indication of its
            willingness to grant patent licenses to such patent claims in a manner consistent with
            the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical Committee that produced this deliverable.]</para>

        <para>[OASIS invites any party to contact the OASIS TC Administrator if it is aware of a
            claim of ownership of any patent claims that would necessarily be infringed by
            implementations of this OASIS Standards Final Deliverable by a patent holder that is
            not willing to provide a license to such patent claims in a manner consistent with the
            IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical Committee that produced this OASIS Standards Final
            Deliverable. OASIS may include such claims on its website, but disclaims any
            obligation to do so.]</para>

        <para>[OASIS takes no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual
            property or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation or
            use of the technology described in this OASIS Standards Final Deliverable or the
            extent to which any license under such rights might or might not be available;
            neither does it represent that it has made any effort to identify any such rights.
            Information on OASIS' procedures with respect to rights in any document or deliverable
            produced by an OASIS Technical Committee can be found on the OASIS website. Copies of
            claims of rights made available for publication and any assurances of licenses to be
            made available, or the result of an attempt made to obtain a general license or
            permission for the use of such proprietary rights by implementers or users of this
            OASIS Standards Final Deliverable, can be obtained from the OASIS TC Administrator.
            OASIS makes no representation that any information or list of intellectual property
            rights will at any time be complete, or that any claims in such list are, in fact,
            Essential Claims.]</para>

        <para>The name "OASIS" is a trademark of <ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/"
                >OASIS</ulink>, the owner and developer of this document, and should be used only
            to refer to the organization and its official outputs. OASIS welcomes reference to,
            and implementation and use of, documents, while reserving the right to enforce its
            marks against misleading uses. Please see <ulink
                url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/"
                >https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark/</ulink> for above
            guidance.</para>
    </section>
</appendix>
