<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY % base SYSTEM "../docbook/dbgenent.mod">
%base;

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;

]>
<section id="definitionsAndAcronyms">
  <title>Definitions and Acronyms</title>

  <section id="definitions">
    <title>Definitions</title>

    <section id="termsDefinedElsewhere">
      <title>Terms Defined Elsewhere</title>

      <para>This document uses the following terms defined elsewhere:</para>

      <para><emphasis>&lt; Placeholder: terms used in this document that are defined in other
        standards or reference documents should be listed here, with a link to the specific
        version of the defining document. &gt;</emphasis></para>
    </section>

    <section id="termsDefinedInThisDocument">
      <title>Terms Defined in this Document</title>

      <para>This document defines the following terms:</para>

      <variablelist>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Agent</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>any application or tool that generates (creates), reads, edits, writes, processes,
              stores, renders or otherwise handles XLIFF documents.</para>
            <para>Agent is the most general application conformance target that subsumes all other
              specialized user agents disregarding whether they are defined in this specification or
              not.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Enrich</term>
          <term>Enriching</term>
          <listitem>
            <para> the process of associating module and extension based metadata and resources with
              the Extracted XLIFF payload </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <title>Processing Requirements</title>
              <listitem>
                <para>Enriching MAY happen at the time of Extraction. </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <note>
              <para>Extractor knowledge of the native format is not assumed while Enriching.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Enricher</term>
          <term>Enricher Agent</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>any Agent that performs the Enriching process </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extract</term>
          <term>Extraction</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>the process of encoding localizable content from a native content or User Interface
              format as XLIFF payload, so that localizable parts of the content in the source language
              are available for translation into the target language along with the necessary context
              information </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extractor</term>
          <term>Extractor Agent</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>any Agent that performs the Extraction process </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Merge</term>
          <term>Merging</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>the process of importing XLIFF payload back to the originating native format, based
              on the <emphasis>full knowledge</emphasis> of the Extraction mechanism, so that the
              localized content or User Interface strings replace the source language in the native
              format </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Merger</term>
          <term>Merger Agent</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>an Agent that performs the Merge process </para>

            <warning>
              <para> Unless specified otherwise, any Merger is deemed to have the same knowledge of
                the native format as the Extractor throughout the specification. </para>
              <para>Mergers independent of Extractors can succeed, but it is out of scope of this
                specification to specify interoperability for merging back without the full Extractor
                knowledge of the native format. </para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>

        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Modify</term>
          <term>Modification</term>
          <listitem>
            <para> the process of changing core and module XLIFF structural and inline elements that
              were previously created by other Writers </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <title>Processing Requirements</title>
              <listitem>
                <para> XLIFF elements MAY be Modified and Enriched at the same time. </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <note>
              <para>Extractor or Enricher knowledge of the native format is not assumed while
                modifying.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Modifier</term>
          <term>Modifier Agent</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>an Agent that performs the Modification process </para>

          </listitem>

        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Provenance</term>
          <term>Provenance Information</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>information about the nature and origin of the localisation data or process. </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translation</term>
          <term>Translate</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>a rendering of the meaning of the source text, expressed in the target
              language</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Translatable text</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Textual content subject to translation during the translation or localisation process.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Writer</term>
          <term>Writer Agent</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>an Agent that creates, generates, or otherwise writes an XLIFF document for whatever
              purpose, including but not limited to Extractor, Modifier, and Enricher Agents. </para>

            <note>
              <para> Since XLIFF is intended as an exchange format rather than a processing format,
                many applications will need to generate XLIFF documents from their internal processing
                formats, even in cases when they are processing XLIFF documents created by another
                Extractor. </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>


        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="abbreviationsAndAcronyms">
    <title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>

    <para>This document uses the following abbreviations and acronyms:</para>

    <para><emphasis>&lt; Placeholder: abbreviations and acronyms used in this document (e.g. IRI,
      URI, MIME, BCP, IANA) should be listed here with their expanded form. &gt;</emphasis></para>
  </section>
</section>
